<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Guide d'encodage pour l'édition numérique d'égodocuments</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Floriane</forename>
                        <surname>Chiffoleau</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <affiliation>
                        <orgName>INRIA</orgName>
                        <address>
                            <street>2 rue Simone Iff</street>
                            <postCode>75012</postCode>
                            <settlement>Paris</settlement>
                            <country key="FR">France</country>
                        </address>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Le Mans Université</authority>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/deed.en">Attribution 3.0 Unported (CC BY 3.0) </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Ce document est dérivé des <ref target="https://www.berliner-intellektuelle.eu/encoding-guidelines.pdf">guidelines d'encodage</ref>
                    créées pour le projet <ref target="https://www.berliner-intellektuelle.eu">Lettres et textes</ref></p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <div>
                    <head>The Project</head>
                    <p>The DAHN project is a project between the University of the Mans, the EHESS and INRIA, and with the partnership of the Ministry
                        of Higher Education, Research and Innovation. Its goal is to create a program for digital scientific edition of corpus of
                        letter exchanges, with, as a basis, the correspondence of Paul d’Estournelles de Constant, senator of Sarthe and 1909 Nobel
                        Peace Prize. The work is to be made in two steps : first, refreshing an already existing numeric environment to let in that
                        new edition. Then, adding the correspondence of d’Estournelles, while documenting the methodology and the actions made. The
                        first editorial platform (from <ref target="https://www.berliner-intellektuelle.eu">Lettres et Textes</ref>) was first
                        developed between 2010 and 2016 and enabled the creation of a data model that combines genetic edition and named entities
                        network. Though on a precise subject, it was thought to be a generic tool that allows transverse research on egodocuments and
                        printed corpus, from every modern or contemporary period and in all imaginable European situations on those periods.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>About this document</head>
                    <p>This document describes the encoding guidelines and decisions that were made specifically for our project and our editions. It
                        is not a replacement for the original TEI documentation. Rather, it focuses on the way we use TEI elements in order to fit
                        every phenomenon we need to encode. For this reason, only elements that we actually use are described together with exact
                        details on how we use them.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Document Encoding</head>
                <p>This TEI encoding must be adapted to the document format we are going to use on the platform created for the project: ego document.
                    Ego documents are written personal documents such as diaries, memoirs or wills. They usually are dated and signed, which will
                    required some recurrent elements on the encoding.</p>
                <p>For each manuscript, a single XML document is created. This part describes elements appearing in those documents including header
                    and body.</p>
                <div>
                    <head>The header</head>
                    <div>
                        <head><gi>teiHeader</gi></head>
                        <p>As usual, the header comprises the <gi>teiHeader</gi> element. Following the TEI guidelines, the <gi>fileDesc</gi> (the
                            main characteristics of the document), <gi>encodingDesc</gi> (editorial rules), <gi>profileDesc</gi> (information about
                            the content) and <gi>revisionDesc</gi> (the history of the encoding) elements are used in <gi>teiHeader</gi>. Inside the
                            header, descriptions are given in French or English, and German where appropriate.</p>
                        <div>
                            <head>Creating the <gi>fileDesc</gi></head>
                            <p>Within <gi>fileDesc</gi>, there are the following elements: <specList>
                                    <specDesc key="titleStmt"/>
                                    <specDesc key="publicationStmt"/>
                                    <specDesc key="seriesStmt"/>
                                    <specDesc key="sourceDesc"/>
                                </specList>
                            </p>
                            <div>
                                <head><gi>titleStmt</gi></head>
                                <p>In the mandatory element <gi>titleStmt</gi>, we always encode the title of the document (<gi>title</gi>), authors
                                    and editors (not for letters), and information on its digital version: the funder (<gi>funder</gi>), the head of
                                    the project (<gi>principal</gi>), and, inside as many <gi>respStmt</gi> elements as needed, all other staff
                                    members and contributors who have worked on the digital version of the particular document. In case of letters,
                                    the <gi>title</gi> is structured as follows: “Letter from + name of the sender + to + name of the addressee +
                                    (place, date)”. For example:</p>
                                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                    <title xml:lang="en">Letter from Ludwig Tieck to Friedrich von Raumer (Ziebingen, 30 March 1815)</title>
                                </egXML>
                                <p>In some case, the letter can be numbered by the sender. It is possible to add that number onto the title, which
                                    then would be structured as follows : ”Letter number + number of the letter + from + [...]”.</p>
                                <p>In case of other manuscripts, the <gi>title</gi> element contains the title as written on the manuscript or given
                                    in another form.</p>
                                <p>For letters, we do not use the <gi>author</gi> element. Instead, the sender and the addressee are encoded in
                                        <gi>correspDesc</gi> inside <gi>profileDesc</gi>.</p>
                                <p>For other types of texts, <gi>author</gi> and <gi>editor</gi> may be used. We have decided to use <gi>editor</gi>
                                    only for roles belonging to the original text, i. e. roles that have led to the original text as it is. The role
                                    is specified in the <att>role</att> attribute of <gi>editor</gi>. For roles of digital edition project members, we
                                    use <gi>respStmt</gi> (see below).</p>
                                <p>If there is more than one author or more than one person with the same role, then their names are grouped inside
                                    one <gi>author</gi> or <gi>editor</gi> element, respectively. These are examples of our intended use of the
                                        <gi>author</gi> and <gi>editor</gi> elements: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                        <author>
                                            <persName ref="#p0001">Ludwig Tieck</persName>
                                        </author>
                                        <editor role="annotator">
                                            <persName ref="#p0002">Wilhelm Heinrich Wackenroder</persName>
                                            <persName ref="#p0003">Another annotator</persName>
                                        </editor>
                                        <editor role="literary_executor">
                                            <persName ref="#p0004">Rudolf Köpke</persName>
                                        </editor>
                                    </egXML></p>
                                <p>The <gi>funder</gi> element must contains the name of the person or organism that finance the project.</p>
                                <p>The <gi>principal</gi> element must contains the name of the person responsible for the creation of the encoding.
                                    It contains detailed elements (forename, surname, and the complete address of the affiliation). </p>
                                <p>The next item <gi>respStmt</gi> comprises the declaration of all persons who took part in the research and edition
                                    of the encoded document. We have selected five different responsibilities: “edited by”, “prepared by”, “in
                                    collaboration with”, “with help from” and “digitization by”. </p>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head><gi>publicationStmt</gi></head>
                                <p>The <gi>publicationStmt</gi> element typically contains all information about the publisher, the publication place
                                    and date and the restrictions of its use. At least, three tags are required to encode the document:
                                        <gi>authority</gi> (organization or person responsible for the publication of the project),
                                        <gi>availability</gi> (licence for the project) and <gi>date</gi> (publication of the project).</p>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head><gi>seriesStmt</gi></head>
                                <p>The <gi>seriesStmt</gi> element groups information about the series or collection to which the document belongs.
                                    For our two example cases, it would coincide with the name of the projects the documents are link to, either
                                    “Letters and texts from intellectual Berlin around 1800” or "Correspondence of Paul d'Estournelles de Constant".
                                    We also specify genre and topic of each document. To do so, we use <att>type</att> attributes with the values
                                        <val>main</val> for the name of the edition, <val>genre</val> for genre and <val>topic</val> for topic. Genre
                                    and topic may appear more than once. For example: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                        <seriesStmt>
                                            <title type="main">Letters and texts from intellectual Berlin around 1800</title>
                                            <title type="genre">Letters</title>
                                            <title type="genre">Logs/reports</title>
                                            <title type="topic">Berlin University</title>
                                        </seriesStmt>
                                    </egXML></p>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head><gi>sourceDesc</gi></head>
                                <p> The following element, <gi>sourceDesc</gi>, is used for all metadata describing the sources of the digital
                                    edition. This element is repeatable, so one could describe different sources if one TEI document for the digital
                                    edition is based on several manuscripts. The documents we are encoding are personal documents, letters or others,
                                    handwritten or typescript depending on the period. For this reason, the <gi>sourceDesc</gi> element always
                                    contains the sub-element <gi>msDesc</gi>, which is intended for the description of manuscripts. If the manuscript
                                    is a letter, it also contains <gi>correspDesc</gi> to identify the sender and addressee. </p>
                                <div>
                                    <head><gi>msDesc</gi></head>
                                    <p>The <gi>msDesc</gi> element contains the following elements. The first four are mandatory, <gi>additional</gi>
                                        is optional. <specList>
                                            <specDesc key="msIdentifier"/>
                                            <specDesc key="msContents"/>
                                            <specDesc key="physDesc"/>
                                            <specDesc key="history"/>
                                            <specDesc key="additional"/>
                                        </specList></p>
                                    <div>
                                        <head><gi>msIdentifier</gi></head>
                                        <p>In the <gi>msIdentifier</gi> element, all information concerning the institution, the manuscript’s
                                            collection and its identifier (<gi>idno</gi>) is placed. A <att>type</att> attribute for <gi>idno</gi> can
                                            be used to be more specific about who gave this identifier. It is necessary to differentiate between the
                                                <gi>repository</gi> and the <gi>institution</gi> element. Institution represents the conservation
                                            place, while repository represents the department in it where the document is preserved. The expected
                                            content for this part has also been modified (in the <gi>schemaSpec</gi> below) in order to be more
                                            accurate with the physical adress of the manuscript's institution. For example: <egXML
                                                xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                                <msIdentifier>
                                                    <location>
                                                        <address>
                                                            <street>9 rue Christian Pineau</street>
                                                            <postCode>72100</postCode>
                                                            <settlement>Le Mans</settlement>
                                                            <region>Pays de la Loire</region>
                                                            <country key="FR">France</country>
                                                        </address>
                                                    </location>
                                                    <institution ref="#ADSarthe">Archives départementales de la Sarthe</institution>
                                                    <repository>Fonds des archives privées</repository>
                                                    <collection>Fonds d'Estournelles de Constant</collection>
                                                    <idno>12 J</idno>
                                                </msIdentifier>
                                            </egXML></p>
                                    </div>
                                    <div>
                                        <head><gi>msContents</gi></head>
                                        <p>The only sub-element of <gi>msContents</gi> is <gi>msItem</gi>. We use it for three different purposes.</p>
                                        <p>First, the document date may be given inside <gi>docDate</gi>. This is the date originally written on the
                                            letter or manuscript by the author<note>If a date was written by a different person, for example by an
                                                archivist, it is not included in <gi>docDate</gi></note>. It may be identified as incorrect and thus
                                            differ from the <gi>origDate</gi> (origin date) in the <gi>history</gi> section, where the actual date
                                            (which can be a supposition) is declared. If no date is given on the manuscript, then <gi>docDate</gi> is
                                            left out and only <gi>origDate</gi> appears in the header. If <gi>docDate</gi> and <gi>origDate</gi> are
                                            the same, then both still appear.</p>
                                        <p>Second, <gi>msItem</gi> may be used to give a summary of the manuscript or other details written by a
                                            project member in one or more <gi>note</gi> elements with the <att>resp</att> attribute. For one of our
                                            project, we use it to declare an annex, if one is present in the document.</p>
                                        <p>Third, <gi>msItem</gi> may be used to give keywords for the manuscript. They are also included inside
                                                <gi>note</gi> elements—one for each keyword—with <att>resp</att> and
                                                <att>type</att>=<val>keyword</val>.</p>
                                        <p>Here is an example including all three cases : <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                                <msContents>
                                                    <msItem>
                                                        <docDate when="1919-02-04"/>
                                                        <note resp="#floriane.chiffoleau">This letter is joined with an annex.</note>
                                                        <note type="keyword" resp="#floriane.chiffoleau">President Wilson</note>
                                                    </msItem>
                                                </msContents>
                                            </egXML></p>
                                    </div>
                                    <div>
                                        <head><gi>physDesc</gi></head>
                                        <p><gi>physDesc</gi> comprises the physical description of the manuscript. In our case, <gi>physDesc</gi> may
                                            contain three to six elements: <specList>
                                                <specDesc key="objectDesc"/>
                                                <specDesc key="handDesc"/>
                                                <specDesc key="accMat"/>
                                                <specDesc key="additions"/>
                                                <specDesc key="sealDesc"/>
                                                <specDesc key="decoDesc"/>
                                            </specList></p>
                                        <p>In the <gi>objectDesc</gi> element, the material, the dimensions, the state of conservation etc. of the
                                            manuscript are specified and are grouped inside <gi>supportDesc</gi>. Those information are available in
                                            different languages: English is required to help with the comprehension of the metadata and others, to
                                            match with the language of the corpus or not. In each tag, the tag used to specified the language can be
                                            the parent tag or a <gi>p</gi>, according to the rules of the TEI Guidelines, joined with an attribute
                                                <att>xml:lang</att>.</p>
                                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                            <objectDesc>
                                                <supportDesc>
                                                    <support>
                                                        <material>
                                                            <material xml:lang="de">Geripptes Papier mit Wasserzeichen.</material>
                                                            <material xml:lang="en">Laid paper with water mark.</material>
                                                            <material xml:lang="fr">Papier finement côtelé comportant un filigrane.</material>
                                                        </material>
                                                    </support>
                                                    <extent>
                                                        <measure type="folio">
                                                            <measure xml:lang="de">1 Bogen, 2 Blatt</measure>
                                                            <measure xml:lang="en">1 sheet of paper, 2 folios</measure>
                                                            <measure xml:lang="fr">2 feuillets</measure>
                                                        </measure>
                                                        <dimensions unit="cm">
                                                            <height>...</height>
                                                            <width>...</width>
                                                        </dimensions>
                                                    </extent>
                                                    <foliation corresp="#pencil">
                                                        <p xml:lang="de">Foliierung eines Archivars mit Bleistift.</p>
                                                        <p xml:lang="en">Foliation by the archive, in pencil.</p>
                                                        <p xml:lang="fr">Numérotation des pages par les archives, crayon de papier.</p>
                                                    </foliation>
                                                    <foliation corresp="#blue_pen">
                                                        <p xml:lang="de">Foliierung eines Archivars mit blauem Stift.</p>
                                                        <p xml:lang="en">Foliation with blue pen by the archive.</p>
                                                        <p xml:lang="fr">Numérotation des pages par les archives, au crayon bleu.</p>
                                                    </foliation>
                                                    <condition>
                                                        <p xml:lang="de">Guter Erhaltungszustand, Faltspuren, Spuren der Aktenbindung. Auf dem zweiten
                                                            Blatt Loch im Papier durch Siegelausriss, Ausschnitt.</p>
                                                        <p xml:lang="en">In a good state of preservation, traces of folding and binding. On second
                                                            folio hole due to tear by seal, cutting.</p>
                                                        <p xml:lang="fr">En bon état. Quelques traces de plis. Déchirure au niveau du sceau.</p>
                                                    </condition>
                                                </supportDesc> ... </objectDesc>
                                        </egXML>
                                        <p><gi>foliation</gi> contains descriptions of foliations. The <att>corresp</att> attribute links each
                                            foliation with the hand who made it (as described by a <gi>handNote</gi>) or— only if it is made by
                                            us—with the corresponding person in the index of project members.</p>
                                        <p>In a letter or some personal document, you may find letterhead or pre-printed element on the support. The
                                            choice was made to describe those element on the <gi>layoutDesc</gi>, inside a <gi>layout</gi> tag with an
                                            attribute and then in <gi>p</gi> tag with attribute for the language. It will then be presented and linked
                                            in the <gi>body</gi>, inside a <gi>fw</gi> element, as it was proposed on one of the article from <ref
                                                target="https://encoding-correspondence.bbaw.de/v1//">Encoding Correspondence</ref>.</p>
                                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                            <objectDesc> ... <layoutDesc>
                                                    <layout xml:id="lh-senat">
                                                        <p xml:lang="fr">Un en-tête, où est écrit "Sénat" en majuscule et souligné, est imprimé en
                                                            haut à gauche de la première feuille de la lettre.</p>
                                                        <p xml:lang="en">A letterhead, where an underlined uppercased "Sénat" is written, is printed
                                                            on the top left of the first folio of the letter.</p>
                                                    </layout>
                                                </layoutDesc>
                                            </objectDesc>
                                        </egXML>
                                        <p>The <gi>handDesc</gi> element is also part of <gi>physDesc</gi>. Here, the different hands found in the
                                            manuscript can be identified and described with as many <gi>handNote</gi> elements as needed. More than
                                            one <gi>handNote</gi> element can belong to the same person: if an author completed a text after a long
                                            time, two different hands could be identified for him.</p>
                                        <p><gi>handNote</gi> is also used to describe which scripture the hand uses predominantly. The following
                                            attributes are used : <list>
                                                <item><att>xml:id</att>: An identifier of the hand.</item>
                                                <item><att>scope</att>: The hand’s preponderance in this manuscript.</item>
                                                <item><att>medium</att>: Which instrument has the hand been using?</item>
                                                <item><att>scribeRef</att>: Points to the person responsible for the hand, i.e. to the respective
                                                        <gi>person</gi> element in the index of persons. This attribute is always given, even if the
                                                    person is the author/sender. If the hand is of an archivist that cannot be identified as a person,
                                                    then this attribute points to the corresponding archive in the index of organizations.</item>
                                                <item><att>scribe</att>: The function that the person has in this particular text.</item>
                                                <item><att>corresp</att>: Only used with <att>scribe</att>="<val>publisher</val>" (see list
                                                    below).</item>
                                            </list>. Similar to what we already explain for the preceeding tags, each hand must be described inside a
                                                <gi>p</gi> tag and with a language attribute.</p>
                                        <p>In the TEI header:<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                                <handDesc>
                                                    <handNote medium="black_ink" scope="major" scribe="author" scribeRef="#p0133" xml:id="major_hand">
                                                        <p xml:lang="de">Hand des Absenders Ludwig Tieck, Brieftext in schwarzer Tinte, vorwiegend in
                                                            Kurrentschrift.</p>
                                                        <p xml:lang="fr">Main de l'expéditeur Ludwig Tieck, corps de la lettre, encre noire, écriture
                                                            majoritairement gothique.</p>
                                                        <p xml:lang="en">Hand of sender Ludwig Tieck, letter text in black ink, mainly German
                                                            script.</p></handNote>
                                                    <handNote medium="red_ink" scope="minor" scribe="addressee" scribeRef="#p0187" xml:id="red_hand">
                                                        <p xml:lang="de">Wahrscheinlich Hand von Friedrich von Raumer zur Zeit der Vorbereitung für
                                                            den Druck, Beschriftung des Briefs auf der ersten Seite in rot.</p>
                                                        <p xml:lang="fr">Probablement la main de Friedrich von Raumer lors de sa préparation du
                                                            manuscrit pour la publication, quelques annotations à l'encre rouge.</p>
                                                        <p xml:lang="en">Very likely Hand of Friedrich von Raumer at the time when he prepared his
                                                            edition of this letter; few remarks and deletions in red ink.</p></handNote>
                                                    <handNote medium="pencil" scope="minor" scribe="archivist" xml:id="pencil">
                                                        <p xml:lang="de">Hand eines Archivars; Foliierung in Bleistift.</p>
                                                        <p xml:lang="fr">Main de l'archiviste qui a numéroté les pages, crayon de papier.</p>
                                                        <p xml:lang="en">Hand of an archivist in charge of foliation, in pencil.</p></handNote>
                                                </handDesc>
                                            </egXML></p>
                                        <p>Corresponding <att>hand</att> in the body: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                                <note hand="#red_hand" place="inline">Tieck an Raumer</note></egXML>
                                        </p>
                                        <p>There may only be one hand with <att>scope</att>=”<val>major</val>”. This is defined to be the default hand
                                            of the document, i. e. the hand that is active in parts of the body where no <att>hand</att> attribute is
                                            given. All other hands have <att>scope</att>=”<val>minor</val>”. When there is only one hand in the whole
                                            manuscript, <att>scope</att>=”<val>sole</val>” is used instead of <att>scope</att>=”<val>major</val>”.
                                            Then this hand is the default hand, of course. The following values can be used for <att>scribe</att>: <list>
                                                <item><val>author</val>: The hand is of the author/sender.</item>
                                                <item><val>publisher</val>: The hand is of somebody who played a role in publishing the text. In this
                                                    case, the attribute <att>corresp</att> can be used to point to the entry of the corresponding
                                                    publication in the index of works (see example above). </item>
                                                <item><val>commentator</val>: The hand is of a commentator.</item>
                                                <item><val>archivist</val>: The hand is of an archivist (no matter if the archivist person is known by
                                                    name or not—see the description of <att>scribeRef</att> above). </item>
                                                <item><val>copyist</val>: The hand is of a copyist, i.e. a person who copied a manuscript authored by
                                                    somebody else.</item>
                                                <item><val>addressee</val>: In case of letters, the hand is of the addressee (i. e. the person given
                                                    in <tag>correspAction type=”received”</tag>inside <gi>correspDesc</gi>.</item>
                                                <item><val>unknown</val>: The person and role of the hand are unknown.</item>
                                                <item><val>other</val>: The hand is of a person whose role does not fit in the other categories but
                                                    who is not unknown.</item>
                                            </list></p>
                                        <p> Furthermore, <gi>physDesc</gi> may contain <gi>sealDesc</gi> where seals used to close the letter (wax
                                            etc.) are specified.</p>
                                        <p>It can also contain a <gi>additions</gi> element, used to describe any additions made inside the manuscript
                                            and on its pages. <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                                <additions>
                                                    <p xml:lang="fr">L'institution qui conserve ce fond a apposé sur toutes les feuilles de textes,
                                                        généralement dans la marge, un tampon où il est inscrit : <stamp resp="#stamp">Archives de la
                                                            Sarthe <lb/>Propriété publique</stamp>.</p>
                                                    <p xml:lang="en">The institution that held the collection applied on each folio, usually in the
                                                        margin, a stamp where it is written: <stamp resp="#stamp">Archives de la Sarthe <lb/>Propriété
                                                            publique</stamp>.</p>
                                                </additions>
                                            </egXML></p>
                                        <p>Any material accompanying the letter—for example an envelope, a picture, a drawing etc.—is described inside
                                                <gi>physDesc</gi> using the <gi>accMat</gi> element. Envelopes are usually regarded as part of the
                                            manuscript pages and are transcribed like normal pages but are being pointed to from <gi>accMat</gi>.
                                                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                                <accMat>
                                                    <p xml:lang="fr">La lettre est accompagnée d'une annexe de six pages.</p>
                                                    <p xml:lang="en">The letter also contains a six pages annex.</p>
                                                </accMat>
                                            </egXML></p>
                                    </div>
                                    <div>
                                        <head><gi>history</gi></head>
                                        <p>After the <gi>physDesc</gi> element, we can now take a look at the <gi>history</gi> element inside
                                                <gi>msDesc</gi>. The full history of a manuscript is described here:</p>
                                        <p>from its creation until today (going through the place and date of creation, the provenance, the
                                            acquisition...). Two child elements can be used: <gi>origin</gi> and <gi>acquisition</gi>.</p>
                                        <p><gi>origin</gi> describes at least the place of creation of the manuscript (inside <gi>origPlace</gi> ) and
                                            its date of creation (inside <gi>origDate</gi>). Further information may be added.</p>
                                        <p> The actual date of creation may differ from any date written on the manuscript, <gi>origDate</gi> contains
                                            a date that is either identified as correct or is a supposition, <gi>docDate</gi> appearing inside
                                                <gi>msItem</gi> contains a date written on the manuscript even if that is incorrect. If
                                                <gi>origDate</gi> and <gi>docDate</gi> are the same, both still appear. For example: <egXML
                                                xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                                <history>
                                                    <origin><p xml:lang="de">Der Brief wurde in <origPlace ref="#l0066">Ziebingen</origPlace> am
                                                                <origDate when-iso="1815-03-30">30. März 1815</origDate> verfasst.</p>
                                                        <p xml:lang="fr">la lettre a été composée à <origPlace ref="#l0066">Ziebingen</origPlace> le
                                                                <origDate when-iso="1815-03-30">30 mars 1815</origDate>.</p>
                                                        <p xml:lang="en">The letter was composed in <origPlace ref="#l0066">Ziebingen</origPlace> on
                                                                <origDate when-iso="1815-03-30">30th March 1815</origDate>.</p></origin> ...
                                                </history>
                                            </egXML></p>
                                        <p><gi>acquisition</gi> records how the manuscript entered the institution that is currently holding it:
                                                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                                <acquisition>
                                                    <p xml:lang="de">Der Nachlass 239 (<persName ref="#p0248">L. de La Foye</persName>) wurde im <date
                                                            when-iso="1990-05">Mai 1990</date> als Teilnachlass mit Mitteln des Bundesministeriums des
                                                        Innern von der Galerie Gerda Bassenge (Berlin, Auktion 55, Teil 1, <date
                                                            when-iso="1990-05-02/04">2.-4.5.1990</date>, Nr. 3009) erworben. Er ist Eigentum der
                                                        Bundesrepublik Deutschland und als Dauerleihgabe der Staatsbibliothek zu Berlin übergeben
                                                        worden.</p>
                                                    <p xml:lang="en">The <persName ref="#p0248">de La Foye</persName> papers (NL 239) were acquired by
                                                        the State Library in <date when-iso="1990-05">May 1990</date> (auction 55 of the Galerie Gerda
                                                        Bassenge, Berlin, part 1, <date when-iso="1990-05-02/04">2.-4.5.1990</date>, Nr. 3009). They
                                                        were funded by the German Ministry of Inner Affairs and loaned to the State Library.</p>
                                                    <p xml:lang="fr">Les papiers <persName ref="#p0248">de La Foye</persName> (NL 239) ont été acquis
                                                        par le ministère allemand de l'intérieur lors de la vente aux enchères organisée par la
                                                        Galerie Gerda Bassenge en <date when-iso="1990-05">mai 1990</date> (Berlin, enchère 55, partie
                                                        1, <date when-iso="1990-05-02/04">2.-4.5.1990</date>, No. 3009). Ils sont la propriété de
                                                        l'État allemand, qui les a confiés sous la forme d'une prêt durable à la Librairie d'État de
                                                        Berlin.</p>
                                                </acquisition>
                                            </egXML></p>
                                    </div>
                                    <div>
                                        <head><gi>additional</gi></head>
                                        <p>The optional element <gi>additional</gi> is the last sub-element of <gi>msDesc</gi> and is currently only
                                            used to hold a <gi>listBibl</gi> describing publications that are in some way related to the manuscript.
                                            These are usually earlier prints of the manuscript but could also be other works where text portions
                                            appearing in the manuscript were published. Each publication is given in a <gi>bibl</gi> element and then
                                                <gi>bibl</gi> sub-elements with <att>xml:lang</att> attribute (the paragraph tag <gi>p</gi> is not
                                            allowed). The tag contains a short bibliographic description, usually using <gi>title</gi> and
                                                <gi>persName</gi> elements. Full descriptions are given in the index of works and are being pointed to
                                            using <att>ref</att> of <gi>title</gi>. <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                                <additional>
                                                    <listBibl>
                                                        <bibl><bibl xml:lang="de"><persName ref="#p0261">Riegel</persName> (1934): <title
                                                                    ref="#w00253">Correspondance d'Adelbert de Chamisso, Fragments inédits</title>,
                                                                Brief 42.</bibl>
                                                            <bibl xml:lang="en"><persName ref="#p0261">Riegel</persName> (1934): <title ref="#w00253"
                                                                    >Correspondance d'Adelbert de Chamisso, Fragments inédits</title>, Letter
                                                                42.</bibl>
                                                            <bibl xml:lang="fr"><persName ref="#p0261">Riegel</persName> (1934): <title ref="#w00253"
                                                                    >Correspondance d'Adelbert de Chamisso, Fragments inédits</title>, Lettre
                                                                42.</bibl></bibl>
                                                        <bibl> ... </bibl>
                                                    </listBibl>
                                                </additional>
                                            </egXML></p>
                                    </div>
                                </div>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Creating the <gi>encodingDesc</gi></head>
                            <p>After <gi>fileDesc</gi>, the second top-level portion of the header is <gi>encodingDesc</gi> . It comprises
                                    <gi>projectDesc</gi> (which simply names the respective project) and <gi>editorialDecl</gi>.</p>
                            <p>The <gi>editorialDecl</gi> element is used for documenting decisions concerning corrections (<gi>correction</gi>) and
                                hyphenation (<gi>hyphenation</gi>) in the manuscript. <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                    <encodingDesc>
                                        <projectDesc>
                                            <p xml:lang="fr">L'encodage de ce document s'est fait dans le cadre du projet DAHN d'"Éditions numérique
                                                de manuscrits historiques (correspondances)".</p>
                                            <p xml:lang="en">The encoding of this document is part of the DAHN Project "Digital Editions of historical
                                                manuscripts (correspondences)".</p>
                                        </projectDesc>
                                        <editorialDecl>
                                            <correction>
                                                <p xml:lang="fr">Aucune correction</p>
                                                <p xml:lang="en">No correction</p>
                                            </correction>
                                            <hyphenation eol="all" rend="sh">
                                                <p xml:lang="fr">Toutes les coupures de mots pour fin de ligne (indiquées principalement avec un tiret
                                                    simple) ont été conservées.</p>
                                                <p xml:lang="en">All the end-of-line hyphenation (made with a single hyphen) have been kept.</p>
                                            </hyphenation>
                                        </editorialDecl>
                                    </encodingDesc>
                                </egXML></p>
                            <p> We usually do not do any normalization and we can do some corrections that is explained in <gi>correction</gi> and are
                                demonstrate later, in the <gi>body</gi> part.</p>
                            <p>The attribute for <gi>hyphenation</gi> differs according to the kind of texts that we have, because its presence and
                                format depends on the author. When present, it always has the attribute <att>eol</att>=”<val>all</val>” which—as
                                specified in the TEI guidelines—describes the way we deal with end-of-line hyphenation (see also the description of
                                    <gi>lb</gi>). Furthermore, it needs the attribute <att>rend</att> where we state which is the default hyphenation
                                character in the manuscript, i. e. the one which appears most often (here, the ”sh” means a single hyphen (”-”)). It
                                uses the same values as the <att>type</att> attribute of <gi>lb</gi>. The <att>type</att> attribute of <gi>lb</gi> is
                                only mandatory if the hyphenation character in the specific case differs.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Creating the <gi>profileDesc</gi></head>
                            <div>
                                <head><gi>correspDesc</gi></head>
                                <p><gi>profileDesc</gi> is used for two purposes. For letters, it contains <gi>correspDesc</gi>. Here, the sender and
                                    addressee are identified using the sub-element <gi>correspAction</gi> and a corresponding attribute:
                                        <att>type</att>=<val>"sent"</val> for the sender and <att>type</att>=<val>"received"</val> for the addressee.
                                    If applicable, previous and following letters are referenced by their file names in our edition using
                                        <gi>correspContext</gi>. For example: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                        <correspDesc>
                                            <correspAction type="sent">
                                                <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/34463780/">Ludwig Tieck</persName>
                                                <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/3101255">Ziebingen</placeName>
                                                <date when-iso="1815-03-30"/>
                                            </correspAction>
                                            <correspAction type="received">
                                                <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/64809232/">Friedrich von Raumer</persName>
                                            </correspAction>
                                            <correspContext>
                                                <ref target="Brief02TieckanRaumer.xml" type="next"/>
                                            </correspContext>
                                        </correspDesc>
                                    </egXML></p>
                                <p> For the sending side, the originating place is also given, as is the date. For the receiving side, this is usually
                                    not the case. However, if the information is given, it should be included. Currently, the place and date are
                                    doubled in <gi>msItem</gi>, <gi>history</gi> and <gi>dateline</gi>, respectively.
                                    <!-- It is unclear whether this policy will be kept in
                                    the future.-->
                                </p>
                                <p>In this part of the encoding, instead of using the references encoded in their corresponding index, we put
                                    identifier from authority file like Geonames and VIAF, to be compatible with the standard of the Correspondence
                                    Metadata Interchange Format (CMIF) and then be findable via <ref target="https://correspsearch.net"
                                        >correspSearch</ref>.</p>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head><gi>langUsage</gi></head>
                                <p>Inside <gi>profileDesc</gi>, we also specify the languages of the manuscript in <gi>langUsage</gi> : <egXML
                                        xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                        <langUsage>
                                            <language ident="de" usage="80"/>
                                            <language ident="fr" usage="20"/>
                                        </langUsage>
                                    </egXML></p>
                                <p>Each langage is identified in a <gi>language</gi> element.The approximate percentage of language usage is given in
                                    the attribute <att>usage</att>. When there is only one language, usage becomes 100, of course. In those cases,
                                        <att>usage</att> may be left out.</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Creating the <gi>revisionDesc</gi></head>
                            <p><gi>revisionDesc</gi> is the last direct child element of <gi>teiHeader</gi>. It summarizes the revision history of the
                                file which is given in English only. Each revision is recorded in a <gi>change</gi> element with a <att>who</att>
                                attribute which refers to the <att>xml:id</att> attribute of the corresponding <gi>person</gi> entry within the index
                                of contributors. <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                    <revisionDesc>
                                        <change when-iso="2012-06-04" who="#anne.baillot">Updated the transcription and added all the elements in
                                            English and French (in the header and in the notes in the body).</change>
                                        <change when-iso="2012-04-02" who="#anne.baillot">Updated a few details.</change>
                                        <change when-iso="2012-03-26" who="#anne.baillot">Finished encoding, revised header, added comparison with
                                            print version.</change>
                                        <change when-iso="2012-03-16" who="#anne.baillot">First encoding (up to line 208). Have to check published
                                            letters before proceeding with the transcription; the text sounds familiar.</change>
                                    </revisionDesc>
                                </egXML></p>
                            <p>The <gi>revisionDesc</gi> will also be used, in our documents, to indicate the level of finalization of the encoding
                                files published on the platform of our project. We have three level of encoding : <list>
                                    <item>raw transcription</item>
                                    <item>annotation in progress</item>
                                    <item>finalized document</item>
                                </list> Those different steps will be indicated with an attribute <att>status</att> with a value for each of those
                                steps : <list>
                                    <item><val>raw_transcription</val>: the document is simply transcribed</item>
                                    <item><val>annotation_in_progress</val>: the transcription is done and the annotation are in progress</item>
                                    <item><val>final_publication</val>: the document is fully finalized and ready for publication</item>
                                </list></p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The body</head>
                    <p> After <gi>teiHeader</gi>, the element <gi>text</gi> follows. It always contains the <gi>body</gi> of the text. It can
                        sometimes also contains <gi>front</gi> and <gi>back</gi> but it’s less relevant for the egodocuments. Of <gi>body</gi>, the
                        only direct sub-element is a <gi>div</gi>: <tag>div type=”transcription”</tag>. Inside of it, the actual body, i. e. the text
                        of the manuscript appears. </p>
                    <div>
                        <head>Structuring the transcription</head>
                        <div>
                            <head>Paragraphs: <gi>p</gi></head>
                            <p> Paragraphs are included inside <gi>p</gi>. A paragraph is defining as beginning and ending with line breaks.
                                Sometimes, however, the end of a paragraph is not marked by a line break but by leaving an amount of space after the
                                last sentence and having the new paragraph begin on the same line. In these cases, <att>rend</att>=”<val>nolb</val>”
                                is used for the <gi>p</gi> before that space. This indicates that there is no line break after it: <egXML
                                    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                    <p rend="nolb">This paragraph ends without a line break but only with a space.</p>
                                    <p rend="nolb">This one, too.</p>
                                    <p>This paragraph, however, ends with a line break.</p></egXML>
                            </p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Line breaks: <gi>lb</gi></head>
                            <p> All line breaks are tagged with the <gi>lb</gi> element. The way we encode end-of-line <gi>lb</gi> hyphenation is
                                described in the <gi>hyphenation</gi> element in the header. When a word is being split at a line break, we keep the
                                hyphenation character. The text <eg>au développe- ment de la civilisation, est assimilé</eg> thus becomes: <egXML
                                    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">au développe-<lb break="no"/>ment de la civilisation, est
                                    assimilé</egXML>
                            </p>
                            <p>As you can see, we use the attribute <att>break</att>=”<val>no</val>” to denote that there is no new word starting
                                there. In the XML file, there must be no spaces and no line breaks between the <gi>lb</gi> tag and the surrounding
                                letters!</p>
                            <p>However, we retain the information about which hyphenation character is used. For each document, we specify a default
                                end-of-line hyphenation character in the <gi>hyphenation</gi> element, that is the character which is used most often.
                                If the hyphenation character in a specific case differs from the default one, we use the attribute <att>type</att> of
                                    <gi>lb</gi> to denote this. The following values are used for <att>type</att>: <list>
                                    <item><val>sh</val>: single hyphen (“-”).</item>
                                    <item><val>dh</val>: double hyphen (“=”).</item>
                                    <item><val>us</val>: underscore (“_”)</item>
                                    <item><val>none</val>: no hyphenation character at all in the original text.</item>
                                </list></p>
                            <p>Thus, if the default end-of-line hyphenation character is the single hyphen, but one location of the manuscript reads
                                    <eg>Werd ich denn hier nun end= lich etwas finden?</eg> then it becomes: <egXML
                                    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">Werd ich denn hier nun end=<lb break="no" type="dh"/>lich etwas
                                    finden?</egXML></p>
                            <p>In the rare case that the line after the break needs to be indented for whatever reason, values for <att>rend</att>
                                have been defined. Use <tag>lb rend=”indent”</tag> for indentation as such without specifying how deep it is, or
                                    <att>rend</att>=”<val>indent-1</val>”, <att>rend</att>=”<val>indent-2</val>” and so on if you need more than one
                                level of indentation: indent-1 then means lowest, the highest number means highest level of indentation.</p>
                            <p>Another rare case is that a character appears after a line break that is not part of the text. See this example:
                                    <eg>"Les dirigeants du monde ont pensé aux relations entre les "gouvernements ;</eg> Here, a quotation mark
                                appears at the beginning of each line (i. e. after each break), but it is not part of the text and thus must, for
                                example, not appear in a display version . This is indicated by using a special value for <att>rend</att> with
                                    <gi>lb</gi>: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><lb rend="after:&quot;"/> Les dirigeants du monde ont
                                    pensé aux relations entre les<lb rend="after:&quot;"/> gouvernements ;</egXML> The value “after:&quot;” means that
                                the character “&quot;” appears after the line break. It is also possible to use <tag>lb rend=”before:X”</tag> for
                                special characters that appear before the line break. Normally, line breaks are only shown in a display version of the
                                transcription (the diplomatic version). In the unusual case where a line break that is marked with <gi>lb</gi> should
                                also be shown in a reading version, <tag>lb rend=”both”</tag> may be used.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Page breaks and facsimilies: <gi>pb</gi></head>
                            <p>The only element which refers to the picture is the page break element <gi>pb</gi>. Each <gi>pb</gi> has a <att>n</att>
                                attribute which indicates the page number. For technical reasons it is required to always start with page number 1.
                                The differing page number of an archivist etc. must be marked up as a note. The <att>facs</att> attribute is used to
                                link to the picture on the server. The first child element of <tag>div type=”transcription”</tag> must be
                                <gi>pb</gi>!</p>
                            <p>For example: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                    <body>
                                        <div type="transcription">
                                            <pb n="1" facs="00000356.jpg"/>
                                            <opener/> ... </div>
                                    </body>
                                </egXML></p>
                            <p> If a word is split at a page break, then the attributes <att>break</att>=”<val>no</val>” and, if necessary,
                                    <att>type</att> are used in exactly the same way as in the <att>lb</att> element for line breaks (see above).
                                Hyphenation characters are also dealt with in the same way as they are in line breaks. See this example: <egXML
                                    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> Werd ich denn hier nun end=<pb n="2" facs="00000357.jpg" break="no"
                                        type="dh"/>lich etwas finden? </egXML></p>
                            <p>Catchwords are included inside <gi>fw</gi> with the attribute <att>type</att>=”<val>catch</val>” : <egXML
                                    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> Werd ich denn hier nun <fw type="catch">end-</fw>
                                    <pb n="2" facs="00000357.jpg"/> endlich etwas finden? </egXML></p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Logical text divisions: <gi>div</gi>, <gi>head</gi>, <gi>trailer</gi></head>
                            <p>For logical text divisions (sections, subsections and so on), we used nested <gi>div</gi> elements. We do not use the
                                numbered division elements <gi>div1</gi>, <gi>div2</gi> and so on. The first <gi>div</gi> of our document will always
                                have an <att>type</att>=”<val>transcription</val>”, but when appropriate, the subsequent <gi>div</gi> may have the
                                attributes <att>type</att> specifying the type of division and <att>n</att> specifying the number of the division.
                                Heading and trailing elements of the section as appearing in the manuscript are given inside <gi>head</gi> and
                                    <gi>trailer</gi>, respectively. These elements always belong only to the <gi>div</gi> of which they are direct
                                sub-elements. For example, if a correspondence is giving a heading with "”Lettre n°” + number of the letter", this can
                                be encoded in a <gi>head</gi> element, as such : <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                    <div type="transcription">
                                        <div type="letter">
                                            <pb facs=".JPG" n="1"/>
                                            <head rend="center underline">LETTRE N° 231.</head> ... </div>
                                    </div></egXML></p>
                            <p>Sometimes, an obvious logical unit of a manuscript can be identified but it has no heading given in the text. In these
                                cases, we can (but do not need to) make up our own heading text. It can be included in <gi>head</gi>, but needs to be
                                inside a <gi>note</gi> with <att>resp</att> : <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><head><note
                                            type="structure" resp="#johanna.preusse">2. Akt</note></head></egXML>
                            </p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Other text divisions: <gi>metamark</gi></head>
                            <p>Sometimes, an author has obviously marked a division in the text that, however, does not belong to a logical unit such
                                as section, subsection and so on, and thus cannot be marked using <gi>div</gi> elements. This division can have
                                different aspects, such as simple lines between two portions of texts or little crosses. To mark this division, we use
                                the element <gi>metamark</gi> with two attributes: <att>function</att> and <att>style</att> (occasionally, we also
                                used the attribute <att>rend</att> to indicate the alignment of the division in the text). The value of
                                    <att>function</att> will always be <val>separation</val>, but the <att>style</att> will often change, according to
                                the kind of sign used to mark this division. Here are few examples of values for <att>style</att>: <list>
                                    <item><val>crosses</val></item>
                                    <item><val>line</val></item>
                                    <item><val>double_line</val></item>
                                    <item><val>dots</val></item>
                                    <item><val>horizontal-rule</val></item>
                                    <item><val>curved-horizontal-rule</val></item>
                                    <item><val>vertical-rule</val></item>
                                    <item><val>X</val></item>
                                </list></p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Structuring the letter/egodocument</head>
                        <p>In every letter or egodocument with similar layout, we use specific elements to encode its opening and closing parts and
                            some other recurring elements.</p>
                        <div>
                            <head>Opener: <gi>opener</gi></head>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="illustrations/contenu-opener.JPG" width="20cm"/>
                            </figure>
                            <p>According to the TEI guidelines, “<gi>opener</gi> groups together dateline, byline, salutation, and similar phrases
                                appearing as a preliminary group at the start of a division, especially of a letter”. We use the <gi>dateline</gi>
                                element to encode the place and the date of the letter, <gi>salute</gi> for the salutation. In some case, it is also
                                possible to have a title for the letter, which can then be included inside the opener, as it is part of the opening of
                                the letter. For example: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                    <opener>
                                        <fw type="letterhead" place="align(left)" corresp="#entete-senat"><hi rend="underline">SÉNAT</hi>
                                        </fw>
                                        <dateline rend="align(right)">
                                            <placeName>Paris</placeName>, <date when-iso="1919-02-04">4 Février 1919</date>
                                        </dateline>
                                        <title rend="align(center)"><hi rend="underline">LE PRÉSIDENT WILSON<lb/> REÇU A LA CHAMBRE DES
                                            DÉPUTÉS</hi></title>
                                        <salute rend="indent">Mon cher Butler,</salute>
                                    </opener>
                                    <opener>
                                        <fw corresp="#lh-senat" place="margin" type="letterhead">
                                            <hi rend="underline">SÉNAT</hi>
                                        </fw>
                                        <dateline rend="align(right)"><placeName>PARIS</placeName>, <date when-iso="1919-02-04">4 Février
                                            1919</date></dateline>
                                        <title rend="align(center) underline">LE PRÉSIDENT WILSON<lb/> REÇU A LA CHAMBRE DES DÉPUTÉS.</title>
                                        <salute rend="indent">Mon cher Butler,</salute>
                                    </opener>
                                </egXML></p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Letterheads : <gi>fw</gi></head>
                            <p>In some letters or other documents, it is possible to find support with letterheads on the first page of the document.
                                This element, already mentioned in the header inside the <gi>layoutDesc</gi> element, will be included in the
                                    <gi>opener</gi>. <figure>
                                    <graphic url="illustrations/exemple-letterhead.JPG" width="20cm"/>
                                </figure> We use the <gi>fw</gi> element, associated with multiple attributes : <att>type</att> indicates that we have
                                a letterhead, <att>place</att> indicate the position of the letterhead on the paper and <att>corresp</att> links it to
                                the <att>xml:id</att> defined in the header (see example above).</p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Closer: <gi>closer</gi></head>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="illustrations/contenu-closer.JPG" width="20cm"/>
                            </figure>
                            <p>Similarly, the TEI guidelines say: “<gi>closer</gi> groups together salutations, datelines, and similar phrases
                                appearing as a final group at the end of a division, especially of a letter”. <gi>salute</gi> may also be used for the
                                final salutations, <gi>signed</gi> for the signature. It is also possible to have a <gi>dateline</gi> at the end of a
                                letter. Postscripts are encoded within the <gi>postscript</gi> element. We only integrate the specified elements in
                                the <gi>closer</gi>, primarily the last salutations. Different (preceding) content in the last paragraph is not part
                                of the <gi>closer</gi>, but of the running text. For example: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                    <closer>
                                        <signed rend="align(right)">Votre affectueusement dévoué</signed>
                                        <address>
                                            <addrLine rend="margin">à Monsieur le Président Nicholas Murray BUTLER,</addrLine>
                                            <addrLine rend="indent">
                                                <hi rend="underline">NEW-YORK.</hi>
                                            </addrLine>
                                        </address>
                                    </closer>
                                    <postscript>
                                        <p rend="margin">1 annexe.</p>
                                    </postscript>
                                </egXML></p>
                            <p>In some cases, it is possible to find multiple <gi>closer</gi> and <gi>postscript</gi>, overlapping one another. In
                                this case, it is possible to have them more than once. For example : <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                    <closer>
                                        <signed rend="align(right)">Votre affectueusement dévoué,</signed>
                                        <signed hand="#annotation" rend="align(right)">d'Estournelles de Constant</signed>
                                    </closer>
                                    <postscript>
                                        <label place="margin">P.S.</label>
                                        <p rend="indent">,- A mon passage à Paris, [...] et pourra sauver le Monde.</p>
                                    </postscript>
                                    <closer>
                                        <signed hand="#annotation" rend="align(right)">E</signed>
                                        <address>
                                            <addrLine rend="margin">à Monsieur le Président Nicholas Murray BUTLER,</addrLine>
                                            <addrLine rend="indent">
                                                <hi rend="underline">NEW-YORK.</hi>
                                            </addrLine>
                                        </address>
                                    </closer>
                                    <postscript>
                                        <p rend="margin">2 annexes.</p>
                                    </postscript>
                                </egXML>
                            </p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Addresses: <gi>address</gi></head>
                            <p> Addresses are not necessarily specific to letters but appear most often in letters. We use the <gi>address</gi>
                                element for denoting addresses appearing on manuscript pages. Its lines are included in <gi>addrLine</gi> elements,
                                without <gi>lb</gi> between them (see the exemple above).</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Displaying changes in the text</head>
                        <div>
                            <head>Changes in the manuscript: <gi>subst</gi>, <gi>del</gi>/<gi>add</gi></head>
                            <p>Our documents are mostly handwritten manuscripts, so they all contain deletions and additions. For these—apart from
                                transpositions (see below)—, we use the element couple of <gi>del</gi> and <gi>add</gi>. If the deletion or addition
                                is made by a different hand than the surrounding text, then these elements are used with the attribute <att>hand</att>
                                pointing to the corresponding <gi>handNote</gi> element in the header: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                    <del rend="strikethrough" hand="#red">Werd ich denn hier nun endlich etwas finden?</del> Ich war <add
                                        place="above" hand="#minor_hand">da</add> zu fremd, um von alle dem Vieles zu verstehen,</egXML></p>
                            <p>For the <att>rend</att> attribute of <gi>del</gi>, the following values are recommended (other values may be used if
                                appropriate): <list>
                                    <item><val>strikethrough</val></item>
                                    <item><val>overwritten</val></item>
                                    <item><val>erasure</val></item>
                                    <item><val>none</val> (e. g. if the deletion is only marked by writing the correct word alongside)</item>
                                </list></p>
                            <p>For the <att>place</att> attribute of <gi>add</gi>, the following values are recommended (other values may be used if
                                appropriate): <list>
                                    <item><val>across</val> (used in combination with <tag>del rend=”overwritten”</tag>) </item>
                                    <item><val>above</val></item>
                                    <item><val>below</val></item>
                                    <item><val>bottom</val></item>
                                    <item><val>top</val></item>
                                    <item><val>margin</val> (may—but does not need to—be more specific: margin-left, margin-right, margin-top,
                                        margin-bottom denote which margin it is, and combining these values with ...-horizontal and ...-vertical
                                        denotes whether the text is written horizontally or vertically (margin-left-horizontal, margin-left-vertical,
                                        margin-right-horizontal and so on).</item>
                                    <item><val>opposite</val></item>
                                    <item><val>overleaf</val></item>
                                    <item><val>end</val></item>
                                    <item><val>inline</val> (if the text is simply written in the line, usually when some text immediately before has
                                        been struck through)</item>
                                    <item><val>inspace</val> (in a predefined space, for example left by an earlier scribe)</item>
                                    <item><val>dots</val> (if the text was first deleted and then marked to be included again by writing dots below
                                        it; see below for examples of nesting of additions and deletions)</item>
                                </list>
                            </p>
                            <p>In case of footnotes or other margin notes that have a numbered or otherwise labeled anchor in the main text, the
                                attribute <att>n</att> may be used with <gi>add</gi> to give the label. In case of strikethrough text, it is sometimes
                                hard to decide how precise to be when encoding a manuscript. Taking a close look at a manuscript page, one can see in
                                many cases that words are actually not completely strikethrough although they are meant to be because the author of
                                course did not use a ruler for striking out. For high precision, the parts (sometimes only one or two letters) that
                                are actually not strikethrough may be marked using <att>rend</att>=”<val>none</val>”:<egXML
                                    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><del rend="none">str</del><del rend="strikethrough">ikethrough
                                    text</del></egXML></p>
                            <p>However, it is left to the encoder to decide whether he really wants to be that precise or simply use
                                    <att>rend</att>=”<val>strikethrough</val>” all the way through. If a passage is stroke out so strongly that it
                                cannot be identified anymore, this is indicated by using <gi>del</gi> in combination with <gi>gap</gi>,
                                    <gi>supplied</gi> or <gi>unclear</gi>. See this example: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><del
                                        rend="strikethrough"><gap reason="strikethrough"/></del></egXML></p>
                            <p>The <gi>subst</gi> element groups a combination of deletion and addition in case they definitely belong together:
                                    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                    <subst>
                                        <del rend="strikethrough">ressener</del>
                                        <add hand="#annotation" place="above">resserrer</add>
                                    </subst>
                                </egXML></p>
                            <p>Sometimes, additions and deletions are nested in themselves: Some text had been added that was (partly) deleted
                                afterwards, or some text had been deleted that was marked for inclusion again afterwards (for example by writing dots
                                below it). For these cases, we use two basic rules<note>For simplicity reasons, <att>rend</att> and <att>place</att>
                                    are missing in the following examples but should always be used, of course.</note>: <list rend="numbered">
                                    <item>What is meant to be final, goes outside: <list>
                                            <item><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><del>A <add>B</add> C</del></egXML> means that “A C”
                                                was written first, then “B” was added in its middle, then everything was deleted.</item>
                                            <item><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><del><add>A</add></del></egXML> means that “A” was
                                                once written as an addition but then, the whole addition was deleted.</item>
                                            <item><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><add><del>A</del></add></egXML> means that “A” was
                                                first deleted but then marked as to be included again.</item>
                                        </list></item>
                                    <item>If rule 1 cannot be obeyed, then the attribute <att>seq</att> is used to denote the sequence of the
                                        additions and deletions: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><add seq="1">A <del seq="2">B</del>
                                                C</add></egXML> means that “A B C” was once written as one large addition but then, the “B” part was
                                        deleted (and not the other way round as it would be if there was no <att>seq</att> attribute).</item>
                                </list></p>
                            <p><att>seq</att> may use higher numbers in case more than two additions and deletions are nested.</p>
                            <p> Sometimes, additions and deletions may also be nested with (parts of) other elements. If, however, an addition or
                                deletion goes over such (parts of) other elements in a way that <gi>add</gi> and <gi>del</gi> cannot be used with
                                proper XML nesting, <gi>addSpan</gi> and <gi>delSpan</gi> are used with the same attributes and with <gi>anchor</gi>.
                                In the unusual case that something was overwritten but it cannot be told which was first and which is the text that
                                was written over it, <att>seq</att>=”<val>0</val>” is used. See this example where a comma and a dash stand in the
                                same place: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                    <subst>
                                        <add seq="0">,</add>
                                        <del seq="0">&#8211;</del>
                                    </subst>
                                </egXML></p>
                            <p>This is a bit of tag abuse because it actually cannot be told which is deleted and which is added, but there are no
                                other elements available. Thus, we use <att>seq</att>=”<val>0</val>” to indicate that actually no sequence can be
                                given.</p>
                            <p>Regarding additions on the margin and footnotes, we have encountered some more unusual cases and errors in the
                                manuscripts and describe them like this: <list>
                                    <item>If there are two margin note marks in the text but only one note on the page (i. e. if the note could either
                                        belong into this or that place), we use a pointer: In one of the places, we give the <gi>add</gi> element an
                                            <att>xml:id</att> and <att>type</att>=”<val>multiple-anchors</val>” : <egXML
                                            xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">text <add xml:id="myID" type="multiple-anchors">addition</add>
                                            text</egXML> In the other place, we use <gi>add</gi> with <att>type</att>=”<val>multiple-anchors</val>”,
                                        too, and inside, there is a <gi>ptr</gi> pointing to the other <gi>add</gi>:<egXML
                                            xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> text <add type="multiple-anchors"><ptr target="#myID"/></add>
                                            text </egXML></item>
                                    <item>If there is a margin note mark in the text but no actual note, we use <gi>add</gi> with
                                            <att>type</att>=”<val>no-anchor</val>” and a non-pointing <gi>ptr</gi>: <egXML
                                            xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">text <add type="no-anchor"><ptr type="none"/></add>
                                        text</egXML></item>
                                </list></p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Textual transpositions: <gi>transpose</gi></head>
                            <p>In some cases, an author has written two or more parts of text which he later decides to give a different order.
                                Sometimes, he does not denote that by deleting the parts and writing them completely again, but by using some mark to
                                denote change of order. For such transpositions, we do not use <gi>subst</gi>, <gi>del</gi> and <gi>add</gi>, but
                                    <gi>transpose</gi>. See this example: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                    <seg xml:id="ib01">dann</seg>
                                    <seg xml:id="ib02">erst</seg>
                                    <listTranspose>
                                        <transpose>
                                            <ptr target="#ib02"/>
                                            <ptr target="#ib01"/>
                                        </transpose>
                                    </listTranspose>
                                </egXML></p>
                            <p>The author has first written “dann erst”, but then decided that it should be “erst dann”. The two parts “dann” and
                                “erst” are included in <gi>seg</gi> elements each with an <att>xml:id</att>. Immediately afterwards, follows with a
                                single <gi>transpose</gi> element containing a pointer (<gi>ptr</gi>) to each part in the order that the author has
                                settled on.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Shift of hand: <gi>handShift</gi></head>
                            <p>Sometimes, the hand changes in a way that cannot be dealt with using the <att>hand</att> attribute with some element.
                                For example, if the author had stopped writing at some point and completed the text on another day using different
                                ink, then this change of hand may obviously not be marked as an addition or a note using <gi>add</gi> or
                                <gi>note</gi>. In those cases, we use the empty element <gi>handShift</gi> to denote a shift of hand: <egXML
                                    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> This part is written in black ink (default hand). <handShift new="#red"
                                    /> This part is written in red ink. </egXML></p>
                            <p>The attribute <att>new</att> points to the corresponding <gi>handNote</gi> element in the header, as does
                                    <att>hand</att> within <gi>add</gi>, <gi>note</gi> or other elements. Please note that <gi>handShift</gi> is meant
                                as a switch that is turned at the point where it appears and never goes back to its original position unless another
                                    <gi>handShift</gi> element appears. This means that <gi>handShift</gi> does not obey XML hierarchies. In following
                                example, the hand “<val>#red</val>” runs until the second <gi>handShift</gi> element appears and does not stop at the
                                closing <gi>hi</gi>: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> This part is written in black ink (default
                                    hand). <hi rend="underline">This part is written in black ink and is underlined<handShift new="#red"/> and this
                                        part is written in red ink and is still underlined.</hi> This part is written in red ink. <handShift
                                        new="#major_hand"/> This part is written in black ink again. </egXML></p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Corrections made by us: <gi>choice</gi>, <gi>sic</gi>/<gi>corr</gi></head>
                            <p>We do not normalize spelling. We do correct syntactical mistakes on the basis of the final text, i. e. with all
                                additions and deletions carried out(<note>Syntactical mistakes usually happen when the author makes additions or
                                    deletions changing the structure of a sentence and does not notice that some word forms needed to be changed,
                                    too.)</note>. For this, <gi>choice</gi> is used with <gi>sic</gi> and <gi>corr</gi>: <egXML
                                    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><choice>
                                        <sic>geworden</sic>
                                        <corr>wurden</corr>
                                    </choice></egXML></p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Abbreviations:<gi>choice</gi>, <gi>abbr</gi>/<gi>expan</gi></head>
                            <p>We expand abbreviations using <gi>choice</gi>, <gi>abbr</gi> and <gi>expan</gi>: <egXML
                                    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                    <choice>
                                        <abbr>phil.</abbr>
                                        <expan>philosophische</expan>
                                    </choice>
                                </egXML></p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Displaying specific parts of the text</head>
                        <div>
                            <head>Dashes and hyphens</head>
                            <p>We differentiate dashes and hyphens the following way: <list>
                                    <item>- is the single hyphen (“-”).</item>
                                    <item>&#11840; is the double hyphen (“=”, not the equal sign)</item>
                                    <item>&#8211; <!--or &ndash;--> is the en-dash (“–”, German “Gedankenstrich”).</item>
                                    <item>&#8212; <!-- or &mdash;--> is the em-dash (“—”).</item>
                                    <item>&#8722; <!--or &minus;--> is the mathematical minus sign.</item>
                                </list> End-of-line hyphenation is treated differently. See below for an explanation of the difference between the
                                numerical and the letter-based (entity) references for the dashes and the minus sign. </p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Special characters</head>
                            <p>Every character available in Unicode can be typed in as-is because all our XML documents are UTF8-encoded. If, however,
                                an encoder cannot type in a character because it is not available on their keyboard, two means of referencing it are
                                possible: <list>
                                    <item>XML numeric character reference <!--&#nnnn;--> where nnnn are up to four decimal digits describing the
                                        Unicode code point of the character.</item>
                                    <item>XML character entity reference <!--&abcde;--> where abcde are letters. We use the character entity
                                        references defined in HTML, although they are not part of XML nor TEI. Currently, we have not defined these
                                        entities in our schema so our documents are not technically valid during editing, but the entity references
                                        are transformed into numeric references before publication.</item>
                                </list> The full list of special characters is given in <ref
                                    target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/
                                    List_of_XML_and_HTML_character_entity_references"
                                    >https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ List_of_XML_and_HTML_character_entity_references</ref></p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Space</head>
                            <p>A non-breaking space is a space that must never be used for a line break. It is denoted by &#160; <!-- or &nbsp;-->:
                                    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">S.&#160;159</egXML></p>
                            <p>Space appearing inside a line for a reason can be denoted using the <gi>space</gi> element: <egXML
                                    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><space extent="two words"/>
                                    <space extent="two words" rend="_"/>
                                    <space extent="two words" rend="&#8211;"/></egXML>
                                <att>extent</att> and <att>rend</att> may be used. The first example denotes an empty space. The second example
                                denotes a space which uses underscores on the manuscript page as placeholders. The third example denotes a space which
                                uses en-dashes. Do not confuse <gi>space</gi> with <gi>gap</gi>: <gi>space</gi> is for space found in a line
                                deliberately placed there by the writer, <gi>gap</gi> is for parts that contain text that cannot be transcribed. </p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Unidentifiable glyphs: <gi>g</gi></head>
                            <p>We have decided not to describe unidentifiable glyphs (i.e. symbols that apparently do not belong to any language) any
                                further because they can be viewed in the facsimile. Instead, we only use <gi>g</gi> with
                                    <att>type</att>=”<val>unknown</val>” to denote that the glyph is there: <egXML
                                    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">text text <g type="unknown"/> text text</egXML></p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Hard-to-read passages: <gi>unclear</gi>, <gi>supplied</gi>, <gi>gap</gi></head>
                            <p>The <gi>unclear</gi> element with the attributes <att>cert</att> and <att>reason</att> is used for passages that are
                                difficult to read: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><unclear cert="medium" reason="stain"
                                    >nur</unclear></egXML> Sometimes, it happens that a hard-to-read passage could be either this or that. In those
                                cases, <gi>unclear</gi> can be used with <gi>choice</gi>: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">der <choice>
                                        <unclear reason="illegible" cert="high">den</unclear>
                                        <unclear reason="illegible" cert="low">dem</unclear>
                                    </choice> Derwisch</egXML></p>
                            <p>Here, it is recommended to use <att>cert</att> to give one possible version a high and the other one a low certainty.
                                    <att>cert</att>=”<val>high</val>” here means, however, that there is a high likelihood for the passage to be the
                                version described—and not that the certainty of unclarity was high. The same goes for
                                <att>cert</att>=”<val>low</val>”, respectively. When the editor could not decide to give one version a higher
                                possibility than the other one, <att>cert</att>=”<val>medium</val>” may be used twice, but this is not recommended.
                                For illegible passages or when a piece of text is missing, we use the <gi>gap</gi> element. It uses the attributes
                                    <att>extent</att> to denote the length of the missing part and <att>reason</att> as does <gi>unclear</gi>, but is
                                an empty element(<note>As opposed to <gi>unclear</gi>, it is mandatory for <gi>gap</gi> to have <att>extent</att>
                                    specified. For <gi>unclear</gi>, the extent can usually be seen from the text that it includes. In rare cases,
                                    however, <att>extent</att> may also be given for <gi>unclear</gi>, for example when it is unsure whether the
                                    unclear part is actually 3 or 4 characters long.</note>): <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><gap
                                        extent="two words" reason="illegible"/></egXML></p>
                            <p>If the editor decides that he knows or can guess the text that is missing, then he may use <gi>supplied</gi> instead of
                                    <gi>gap</gi> to supply the missing text. <gi>supplied</gi> has the same attributes as <gi>unclear</gi>: <egXML
                                    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">leur <supplied reason="stain">raison</supplied> fait</egXML>
                            </p>
                            <p>The difference between <gi>unclear</gi> and <gi>supplied</gi> is that the first is used when the text is hard to read
                                but still legible and the latter is used as a replacement for <gi>gap</gi> when the text is completely illegible or
                                missing. The following values for <att>reason</att> in <gi>unclear</gi>, <gi>gap</gi> and <gi>supplied</gi> are
                                currently recognized in the web interface and translated automatically into German and French for display: <list>
                                    <item><val>border</val>/<val>bound</val>/<val>binding</val></item>
                                    <item><val>crease</val>/<val>folding</val>/<val>folded</val></item>
                                    <item><val>damage</val></item>
                                    <item><val>erasure</val>/<val>strikethrough</val></item>
                                    <item><val>faded</val></item>
                                    <item><val>illegible</val>/<val>not... legible</val></item>
                                    <item><val>hole</val> (without the word seal)</item>
                                    <item><val>incomplete</val></item>
                                    <item><val>lost</val></item>
                                    <item><val>overlapping folio</val></item>
                                    <item><val>overwritten</val></item>
                                    <item><val>paper missing</val></item>
                                    <item><val>seal</val></item>
                                    <item><val>smudged</val></item>
                                    <item><val>stain</val></item>
                                    <item><val>tape</val></item>
                                    <item><val>wax</val></item>
                                </list> Other values may be used if appropriate.</p>
                            <p>Do not confuse <gi>gap</gi> with <gi>space</gi>! <gi>gap</gi> is for parts containing text that cannot be transcribed,
                                    <gi>space</gi> is for space found in a line deliberately placed there by the writer.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Highlighted text: <gi>hi</gi></head>
                            <p>We only use the <gi>hi</gi> element, which, according to the TEI guidelines, “marks a word or phrase as graphically
                                distinct from the surrounding text”. A change of scripture is indicated with <gi>hi</gi>, too (for example if one word
                                is written in “Latin” and the rest of the text in “Kurrent” scripture). We add the <att>rend</att> attribute which can
                                adopt several values. For example: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><hi rend="underline">ils ont oublié
                                        les relations entre les peuples !</hi></egXML>
                            </p>
                            <p>The following values are recommended for <att>rend</att>: <list>
                                    <item><val>underline</val> (with <att>n</att> indicating how often the word is underlined; if n=1, then it may be
                                        left out)</item>
                                    <item><val>superscript</val></item>
                                    <item><val>subscript</val></item>
                                    <item><val>small</val></item>
                                    <item><val>large</val></item>
                                    <item><val>quoted</val></item>
                                    <item><val>majuscule</val></item>
                                    <item><val>latin</val> (if the respective text is written in “Latin” scripture as opposed to “Kurrent” scripture
                                        surrounding it)</item>
                                    <item><val>kurrent</val> (if the respective text is written in “Kurrent” scripture as opposed to “Latin” scripture
                                        surrounding it)</item>
                                    <item><val>mark</val> (if there is a vertical line to mark a part of the text)</item>
                                    <item><val>upsidedown</val></item>
                                </list>
                                <gi>hi</gi> may be used with <att>hand</att> to denote the hand which has done the highlighting if is it not the hand
                                that has written the highlighted text. <att>hand</att> corresponds with <gi>handNote</gi> in header as it does in the
                                    <gi>add</gi> and <gi>note</gi> elements.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Horizontal alignment</head>
                            <p>Almost every element may use the <att>rend</att> attribute to denote its horizontal alignment. See these examples:
                                    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><dateline rend="align(right)">Dresden den 6t October.
                                        23</dateline>
                                        <title rend="align(center)">L'ARMÉE de DEMAIN .</title></egXML></p>
                            <p>The following values are used: <list>
                                    <item><val>align(center)</val> (centered text)</item>
                                    <item><val>align(right)</val> (right-aligned text)</item>
                                </list></p>
                            <p>Left-aligned text is not denoted because it is the default. Apart from that, some elements, for example <gi>hi</gi>,
                                use <att>rend</att> for other purposes. Please note that if because of this, an element has two values for
                                    <att>rend</att>, the following is not allowed because an attribute may not appear more than once for an element in
                                XML: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"
                                    ><!-- WRONG!
                                    <hi rend="kurrent" rend="align(center)">...</hi>--></egXML> This,
                                however, is correct: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><hi rend="kurrent align(center)">...</hi>
                                </egXML></p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Lists: <gi>list</gi></head>
                            <p>Lists should be encoded with the <gi>list</gi> element: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                    <list>
                                        <label>1)</label>
                                        <item>die Rechtslehre,</item>
                                        <lb/>
                                        <label>2)</label>
                                        <item>die philosophischen Briefe,</item>
                                        <lb/>
                                        <label>3)</label>
                                        <item>über die Mythologie,</item>
                                    </list></egXML> The labels given inside the <gi>label</gi> element must really exist in the document. The
                                    <gi>label</gi> element must not be used if they don’t appear in the source. </p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Citations: <gi>cit</gi>, <gi>quote</gi></head>
                            <p>Parts that the author of a manuscript has cited from another source are included in <gi>cit</gi> and <gi>quote</gi>. If
                                no bibliographic reference is given in the manuscript, we write the reference ourselves and include it in a
                                    <gi>note</gi> with <att>resp</att>. See this example: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                    <cit>
                                        <quote>
                                            <lg type="poem">
                                                <l>da nun die Liebe haucht in die Gedanken</l>
                                                <l>Ich werde kunstvoll gut gesetzt an Jahren</l>
                                            </lg>
                                        </quote>
                                        <note resp="#sabine.seifert"><persName ref="#p0237">Chamisso</persName> zitiert aus dem Gedicht <title
                                                ref="#w00260">Erfüllung</title> von <persName ref="#p0249">Karl August Varnhagen von Ense</persName>,
                                            das gedruckt in den <title ref="#w00254">Vermischten Gedichten</title> Varnhagens vorliegt (S. 102). Hier
                                            lautet die letzte Strophe: "Doch nun die Liebe haucht in die Gedanken, / Naht schnell begehrter Ufer ferne
                                            Weite, / Ich werde kunstvoll, gut, gesetzt von Jahren."</note>
                                    </cit>
                                </egXML></p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Dates: <gi>date</gi></head>
                            <p>We place dates in a <gi>date</gi> element and add a standardized form. Two examples: <egXML
                                    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><date when-iso="1823-10-06">den 6t October. 23</date>
                                    <date notBefore="1824" notAfter="1825">1824-1825</date>
                                </egXML></p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Named entitites: Persons, organizations, places, works</head>
                            <p>Every time, a name of a person, an organization, a place or a work appears in a text, it gets marked using
                                    <gi>persName</gi>, <gi>orgName</gi>, <gi>placeName</gi> or <gi>title</gi>, respectively. For every such entity, an
                                entry in the corresponding index is created including an <att>xml:id</att> that has a specific format. From inside the
                                text, the name is linked with the index entry using the <att>ref</att> attribute which points to the corresponding
                                    <att>xml:id</att>. For example: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                    <placeName ref="#l0003">Dresden</placeName>
                                    <orgName ref="#o0001">Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</orgName>
                                    <persName ref="#p0003">Sofokles</persName>
                                    <title ref="#w0010">Nachgelassene Schriften und Briefwechsel</title></egXML></p>
                            <p>However, it sometimes happens that the author writes about a person, an organization, a place or a work without quoting
                                their name. We can’t use the elements <gi>persName</gi>, <gi>orgName</gi>, <gi>placeName</gi> or <gi>title</gi> in
                                those cases, because there is neither a name nor a title. Instead, the <gi>rs</gi> (“referencing string”) element can
                                be applied: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><rs ref="#p0002">Bruder</rs></egXML></p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Parts in different language: <gi>foreign</gi></head>
                            <p>The majority of the documents is written in German or French. We specify the document’s languages in the
                                    <gi>profileDesc</gi> as part of the TEI header.</p>
                            <p> To denote the actual parts of the text written in another language than its main language, we add an
                                    <att>xml:lang</att> attribute to the correspondent element (<gi>div</gi>, <gi>p</gi>, <gi>hi</gi>, ...). If there
                                is no element directly corresponding with the change of language, we use the <gi>foreign</gi> element with
                                    <att>xml:lang</att> as its attribute.</p>
                            <p>As defined in the XML standard, value of the attribute is the code of the language according to IETF’s BCP 47. In our
                                case, it usually has only one part—the code of the language according to ISO 639. For example: <egXML
                                    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><foreign xml:lang="la">malus</foreign></egXML>
                            </p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Using the <gi>note</gi> element</head>
                        <div>
                            <head>Notes: <gi>note</gi></head>
                            <p>We distinguish two types of notes—but use the <gi>note</gi> element for both of them.</p>
                            <p> On the one hand, there are notes that appear on the manuscript page. They can be written by the author/sender himself,
                                by a publisher, by an archivist, and so on. We use the attribute <att>hand</att> to link them to a hand that is
                                described in a <gi>handNote</gi> element. The <att>place</att> attribute can adopt the same values as it can in the
                                    <gi>add</gi> element. Signatures of archives are marked using the <att>type</att> attribute.</p>
                            <p> On the other hand, there are notes that we write ourselves. They do not appear on the manuscript page, of course. For
                                these notes, we do not use <att>hand</att>, but <att>resp</att> to link the note with the person that has written it,
                                i.e. with their entry in the index of contributors. If a note written by us should appear only in one of the two
                                display versions in the web interface, this may be indicated using <att>subtype</att>: <egXML
                                    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><note resp="#sabine.seifert" subtype="1">only in version 1 (Diplomatic
                                        version)</note>
                                    <note resp="#sabine.seifert" subtype="2">only in version 2 (Reading version)</note></egXML></p>
                            <p> Both the <gi>note</gi> and the <gi>add</gi> element may describe additions. As it is difficult to know how to
                                distinguish between cases where <gi>note</gi> should be used and cases where <gi>add</gi> should be used, we have
                                decided that this cannot be told for the whole edition and thus settled on making this decision dependent on the
                                habits of each author—except for two project-wide rules: <list>
                                    <item>If an addition directly and definitely belongs together with a deletion, then <gi>add</gi>, <gi>del</gi> and
                                            <gi>subst</gi> are always used.</item>
                                    <item>For margin notes (those with <att>place</att>=”<val>margin</val>” and so on), <gi>add</gi> is used if the
                                        addition has a determinable anchor in the text, i. e. if it gramatically and/or semantically belongs into a
                                        certain position in the text that can be clearly identified. Otherwise, then <gi>note</gi> is used.</item>
                                </list></p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Foliation numbers: <gi>note</gi></head>
                            <p>We also use the <gi>note</gi> element to denote foliation numbers found on the manuscript page or made by us (e. g. if
                                the foliation on the manuscript is wrong). They are marked using <att>type</att>=”<val>foliation</val>”. As with other
                                notes, they are linked with <att>hand</att> or <att>resp</att>, depending on who made them. For example: <egXML
                                    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                    <note type="foliation" hand="#red">Foliation number on the manuscript page</note>
                                    <note type="foliation" hand="#pencil">Other foliation number on the manuscript page</note>
                                    <note type="foliation" resp="#johanna.preusse">A foliation made by us</note>
                                </egXML></p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Logical text structure: <gi>note</gi></head>
                            <p> Furthermore, the <gi>note</gi> element may be used with <att>type</att>=”<val>structure</val>” to denote numbers or
                                other means of text structuring in a logical way : <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><head><note
                                            type="structure" resp="#johanna.preusse">2. Akt</note></head></egXML></p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Linking entities</head>
                        <div>
                            <head>Pointers inside one manuscript : <gi>ref</gi></head>
                            <p>A different location inside the same manuscript can be referenced by giving the element that is being pointed to an
                                    <att>xml:id</att> and using <gi>ref</gi> with <att>target</att> from another location to point to it. See the
                                example: This is the element that is being pointed to: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><pb n="4"
                                        facs="00000170.jpg" xml:id="Brief001ChamissoandeLaFoye-Blatt4v"/> This is the pointer: <accMat>
                                        <ref target="#Brief001ChamissoandeLaFoye-Blatt4v">Blatt 4v</ref> dient als Briefumschlag. </accMat></egXML> As
                                    <att>target</att> points to a location within the same XML tree, # appears as its first character.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Pointers to other manuscripts of the edition: <gi>ref</gi></head>
                            <p>Other manuscripts of our edition are referenced using <gi>ref</gi> with <att>target</att> containing the file name of
                                the manuscript: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><origin>
                                        <seg xml:lang="de"><persName ref="#p0237">Chamissos</persName> eigenhändige Abschrift dieses Briefes hat
                                            möglicherweise dem Brief an <persName ref="#p0248">de La Foye</persName> (ohne Ort und Datum, <ref
                                                target="Brief027ChamissoandeLaFoye.xml">Bl. 47-48</ref>) beigelegen. Wann Chamisso die Abschrift
                                            anfertigte, ist nicht eindeutig zu bestimmen. </seg> ... </origin>
                                </egXML></p>
                            <p>This may be combined with a pointer to a position inside the other manuscript: <egXML
                                    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><ref target="Boeckh_Buchkatalog.xml#book-4">Nr. 4 im Katalog meiner
                                        Bücher</ref></egXML></p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Pointers to HTTP URLs: <gi>ref</gi></head>
                            <p><gi>ref</gi> with <att>target</att> is also used for pointing to HTTP URLs. This occurs most often in notes that are
                                written by us and in the header. <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                    <note resp="#lena.ebert">Im <ref target="http://woerterbuchnetz.de/DWB/">Deutschen Wörterbuch von Jacob und
                                            Wilhelm Grimm</ref> [Zugriff 17.07.2012] findet man für "Maultasche" auch die Bedeutung
                                            <quote>"klatschender schlag aufs maul"</quote>, in welcher <persName ref="#p0237">Chamisso</persName> das
                                        Wort sicherlich verwendet.</note>
                                </egXML></p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Index encoding</head>
                <p> The digital edition includes five indexes: <list>
                        <item>index of persons</item>
                        <item>index of organizations</item>
                        <item>index of places</item>
                        <item>index of works</item>
                        <item>index of contributors (to the digital edition)</item>
                    </list> One XML document is created for each of the indexes. This is the skeleton of each of the index documents: <egXML
                        xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <teiHeader>
                            <fileDesc>
                                <titleStmt>
                                    <title>Index ...</title>
                                    <funder>Ministère de lʼEnseignement supérieur, de la Recherche et de lʼInnovation (MESRI)</funder>
                                    <principal>
                                        <persName ref="#anne.baillot">
                                            <forename>Anne</forename>
                                            <surname>Baillot</surname>
                                        </persName>
                                        <affiliation>
                                            <orgName ref="#hu.berlin">Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</orgName>
                                            <address>
                                                <street>Unter den Linden 6</street>
                                                <postCode>10099</postCode>
                                                <settlement>Berlin</settlement>
                                                <country key="DE">Deutschland</country>
                                            </address>
                                        </affiliation>
                                    </principal>
                                    <!-- <respStmt>...</respStmt> -->
                                </titleStmt>
                                <publicationStmt>
                                    <publisher>Projet DAHN</publisher>
                                    <availability>
                                        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/deed.en">Attribution 3.0 Unported (CC BY 3.0)
                                        </licence>
                                    </availability>
                                    <date when-iso="...">...</date>
                                </publicationStmt>
                                <seriesStmt>
                                    <title type="main">Correspondances de Paul d'Estournelles</title>
                                </seriesStmt>
                                <sourceDesc>
                                    <p>Born digital</p>
                                </sourceDesc>
                            </fileDesc>
                            <revisionDesc>
                                <change when-iso=" " who="#name.surname">...</change>
                            </revisionDesc>
                        </teiHeader>
                    </egXML>The TEI header is almost identical for all indexes. Please note that the <gi>sourceDesc</gi> element contains only one
                    line: “born digital”, because it originates in a digital form. The indexes are included inside the <gi>body</gi> element, i. e.
                    the elements <gi>listPerson</gi>, <gi>listOrg</gi> and so on are direct sub-elements of <gi>body</gi>.</p>
                <div>
                    <head>Index of persons</head>
                    <p>The index of persons comprises any person appearing in our texts, whether as an author, as an addressee of a letter, otherwise
                        involved or simply mentioned in a manuscript. This index is to be distinguished from the index of contributors listing persons
                        who have worked on this edition, which is explain in another section.</p>
                    <div>
                        <head><gi>listPerson</gi></head>
                        <p>The index consists of a <gi>listPerson</gi> element which contains one <gi>person</gi> element for each person described
                            and one <gi>listRelation</gi> element for describing all relationships between persons. This is the basic structure whose
                            elements are described in more detail below: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                <listPerson>
                                    <person xml:id="...">
                                        <persName>
                                            <forename>...</forename>
                                            <surname>...</surname> ... </persName>
                                        <birth>
                                            <date when-iso="..."/>
                                            <placeName>...</placeName>
                                        </birth>
                                        <death>
                                            <date when-iso="..."/>
                                            <placeName>...</placeName>
                                        </death>
                                        <sex value="1"/>
                                        <occupation>...</occupation>
                                        <education>...</education>
                                        <affiliation>...</affiliation>
                                        <event>...</event>
                                        <idno type="...">...</idno>
                                    </person>
                                    <person xml:id="..."> ... </person>
                                    <listRelation>
                                        <relation name="..." active="... ..." passive="... ..."/>
                                        <relation name="..." mutual="... ... ..."/> ... </listRelation>
                                </listPerson>
                            </egXML></p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head><gi>person</gi></head>
                        <p>Every <gi>person</gi> element has an <att>xml:id</att> attribute used for referencing the person from the manuscript texts
                            and other places whose value is composed of “p” plus four different digits: <egXML
                                xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                <person xml:id="p0001">
                                    <persName>
                                        <roleName type="nobility">Baron</roleName>
                                        <forename>Paul</forename>
                                        <nameLink>d'</nameLink>
                                        <surname>Estournelles de Constant</surname>
                                    </persName>
                                </person>
                            </egXML></p>
                        <p>The following information can be given inside of <gi>persName</gi>: <list>
                                <item><gi>forename</gi> is used for the first name. It can be completed by a <att>type</att> attribute in order to
                                    precise whether this is the name usually used, the second name etc.</item>
                                <item><gi>surname</gi> is used for the family name. It can be completed by a <att>type</att> attribute in order to
                                    precise whether this is a maiden or married name (<att>type</att>=”<val>maiden</val>” or
                                        <att>type</att>=”<val>married</val>”).</item>
                                <item><gi>nameLink</gi> is used for the link in aristocratic names.</item>
                                <item><gi>addName</gi> is used for a nickname or alias.</item>
                                <item><gi>roleName</gi> with <att>type</att>=”<val>honorific</val>” is used to indicate academic titles that are
                                        “<val>Dr.</val>” or on a higher level than that.</item>
                                <item><gi>roleName</gi> with other values of <att>type</att> is used indicate functions such as king, pope,
                                        princess(<note>This role has to be indicated if it’s used as a way to distinctly designate the person and not
                                        be just a role in general</note>)</item>
                                <item><gi>genName</gi> is used in order to distinguish between identical names belonging to different persons (in case
                                    of a difference of generation etc.), for example if there is a number after the first name of kings or the words
                                    “junior” and “senior”.</item>
                            </list> For example: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                <persName>
                                    <forename>Stanislaus</forename>
                                    <genName>II.</genName>
                                    <addName>Augustus</addName>
                                    <surname>Poniatowsky</surname>
                                    <roleName type="nobility">King of Poland <date when-iso="1764/1798">1764-1798</date></roleName>
                                    <roleName type="nobility">Grand Duke of Lithuania</roleName>
                                </persName>
                            </egXML></p>
                        <p>Apart from the name, we encode the following information on persons inside a <gi>person</gi> element:<list>
                                <item>information on birth using <gi>birth</gi> with <gi>date</gi> and <gi>placeName</gi> inside.</item>
                                <item>information on death using <gi>death</gi> with <gi>date</gi> and <gi>placeName</gi> inside.</item>
                                <item>sex using <gi>sex</gi> with <tag>sex value=”1”</tag> for a male person and <tag>sex value=”2”</tag> for a female
                                    person.</item>
                                <item>occupations using the <gi>occupation</gi> element. Any kind of occupation or profession can be encoded here.
                                    Thus, <gi>occupation</gi> may appear more than once.</item>
                                <item>affiliations using the <gi>affiliation</gi> element.</item>
                                <item><gi>orgName</gi> can be used inside this element in order to denote the name of an organization and to provide a
                                    pointer to the corresponding entry in the index of organizations. <gi>placeName</gi> may also be used if
                                    appropriate. <gi>affiliation</gi> can appear more than once.</item>
                                <item>educational experiences using the <gi>education</gi> element. Inside, <gi>placeName</gi> and <gi>orgName</gi>
                                    can be used, too, when appropriate. <gi>education</gi> can appear more than once.</item>
                                <item>other events related to that person using the <gi>event</gi> element.</item>
                                <item><p>authority file number using the <gi>idno</gi> element to reference the person mentionned. Among the authority
                                        file available, you can for example choose the <ref
                                            target="https://www.dnb.de/DE/Professionell/Standardisierung/GND/gnd_node.html">PND Number</ref> which is
                                        maintained by the German National Library or the <ref target="http://viaf.org">VIAF</ref>, which is an
                                        international authority file operated by the Online Computer Library Center.</p></item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>For every element, we can use the attribute <att>cert</att> to indicate the degree of certainty associated with its
                            content. We use the values <val>high</val>, <val>medium</val> and <val>low</val>. When no <att>cert</att> attribute is
                            given, this means that the content is definitely certain.</p>
                        <p>Dates are encoded inside <gi>date</gi> with the appropriate attributes according to the guidelines. Dates inside
                                <gi>birth</gi> and <gi>death</gi> don’t need to be repeated as textual content of the <gi>date</gi> element because
                            for the indices, the textual content is not shown in the web interface anyway.</p>
                        <p>Thus, this is correct: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><birth><date when-iso="1730-08-19"/></birth></egXML>
                            . . . but this is superfluous: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><birth><date when-iso="1730-08-19">19.
                                        August 1730</date></birth></egXML>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head><gi>listRelation</gi>, <gi>relation</gi></head>
                        <p>Relationships between persons are encoded using <gi>relation</gi> elements that appear inside one <gi>listRelation</gi>
                            which is included in <gi>listPerson</gi> after all <gi>person</gi> elements. Here are some examples: <egXML
                                xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                <relation name="parent" active="#p0001 #p0002" passive="#p0003 #p0004"/>
                                <relation name="spouse" mutual="#p0001 #p0002"/>
                                <relation name="lover" mutual="#p0001 #p0006"/>
                                <relation name="teacher" active="#p0006" passive="#p0004"/>
                            </egXML> These examples indicate the following: Persons 1 and 2 are parents of persons 3 and 4. Persons 1 and 2 are also
                            married. Person 1, however, has a lover which is person 6. Person 6 is also a teacher of person 4. </p>
                        <p>Names of relations (in the <att>name</att> attribute) can be chosen as appropriate. For reasons of uniformity, we do not
                            use the inverse relationships “child” (use parent instead) and “student” (use teacher instead).</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Index of organizations</head>
                    <div>
                        <head><gi>listOrg</gi></head>
                        <p>The index of organizations is contained in a <gi>listOrg</gi> element. Inside, there is one <gi>org</gi> element for each
                            organization.</p>
                        <p>It would be better to have two <gi>listOrg</gi> element, containing each a set of organizations. One would contains the
                            organizations mentioned in the corpus that would then be referenced in the corpus. The other would contains the
                            organizations linked to the project and its contributors. It would then be all the organizations mentioned in the index of
                            contributors and the organizations mentioned in the metadata, like the institution where a document from the corpus is
                            stored (in the <gi>msDesc</gi>).</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head><gi>org</gi></head>
                        <p>Every <gi>org</gi> element have <att>xml:id</att>s that are composed of a simplified version of the organisation name, but
                            still identifiable.</p>
                        <p> Inside <gi>org</gi>, there is a <gi>orgName</gi> to specify the name of the organization and its date of creation and it
                            is followed by a <gi>desc</gi> element to present briefly the organization. There is also a <gi>placeName</gi> to localise
                            the organization (the place, the country and the location). Finally, just like for the <gi>person</gi>, there is the
                                <gi>idno</gi> element that links the organization to an authority file. For example :<egXML
                                xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                <org xml:id="carnegie_endowment">
                                    <orgName from-iso="1910">Carnegie Endowment for International Peace</orgName>
                                    <desc>Conducts research programs, discussions, publications on international affairs and the american foreign
                                        policy. Until 1948, it was composed of 3 divisions: Intercourse and education, Economics and history,
                                        International law.</desc>
                                    <placeName from-iso="1910" notAfter-iso="1948">
                                        <placeName>Peter Parker House</placeName>
                                        <country>United States of America</country>
                                        <location>
                                            <geo>38.90931 -77.04112</geo>
                                        </location>
                                    </placeName>
                                    <idno type="VIAF">144086141</idno>
                                </org>
                            </egXML></p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Index of places</head>
                    <div>
                        <head><gi>listPlace</gi></head>
                        <p>The whole index of places is contained in one <gi>listPlace</gi> element. Inside, there is one <gi>place</gi> element for
                            each place. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head><gi>place</gi></head>
                        <p>Places have <att>xml:id</att>s that are composed of “l” (location) plus four digits. It has a <att>type</att> attribute
                            specifiying the type of location (city, country, region...). Inside <gi>place</gi>, at least one name is given inside
                                <gi>placeName</gi>. Other names, for example in different languages, may be added. After that, GPS coordinates for the
                            place are included inside <gi>location</gi> and <gi>geo</gi>. Those coordinates have to be in decimals or a map will not
                            be able to interprate them. Finally, we can also have an <gi>idno</gi> with an attribute
                                <att>type</att>=<val>"geonames"</val> to reference the place with its identifier from the geographical database.</p>
                        <p>See this example of a full entry in the index of places: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><place
                                    type="region" xml:id="l0972">
                                    <placeName xml:lang="en">Sardinia</placeName>
                                    <placeName xml:lang="de">Sardinien</placeName>
                                    <placeName xml:lang="fr">Sardaigne</placeName>
                                    <location>
                                        <geo>40.027778 9.069444</geo>
                                    </location>
                                    <idno type="geonames">2523227</idno>
                                </place></egXML></p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Index of works</head>
                    <p>This index gathers works, monographs, articles, journals ..., shortly all objects that can be described bibliographically.
                        Every title has an <att>xml:id</att> attribute whose value is composed of “w” (work) plus five digits.</p>
                    <div>
                        <head><gi>listBibl</gi></head>
                        <p>The whole index is contained in one <gi>listBibl</gi> element. Inside, there is one element <gi>biblStruct</gi> for each
                            title. The structure of <gi>biblStruct</gi> depends on the type of work. For non-indepedent publications, i. e. articles
                            within a monograph or journal, the basic structure is as follows: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                <biblStruct xml:id="w...">
                                    <analytic>
                                        <author ref="#p...">...</author>
                                        <title>...</title>
                                    </analytic>
                                    <monogr>
                                        <editor ref="#p...">...</editor>
                                        <title ref="#w..." level="...">...</title>
                                        <imprint>
                                            <biblScope unit="volume">...</biblScope>
                                            <biblScope unit="page">...-...</biblScope>
                                            <pubPlace ref="#l...">...</pubPlace>
                                            <publisher>...</publisher>
                                            <date when-iso="..."/>
                                        </imprint>
                                    </monogr>
                                </biblStruct>
                            </egXML>
                            <gi>analytic</gi> contains the <gi>author</gi> and <gi>title</gi> of the article. <gi>monogr</gi> in this case contains
                            information on the independent item inside which the article was published. <gi>editor</gi> is usually used here, it may
                            have a <att>role</att> attribute to specify the role of the person. The <gi>title</gi> inside <gi>monogr</gi> always has
                            the attribute <att>level</att> where the type of publication is specified. <att>level</att>=”<val>j</val>” is used for
                            journals, <att>level</att>=”<val>m</val>” is used for books (monographic title), <att>level</att>=”<val>p</val>” is used
                            for “Seminararbeiten” (non-journal papers made in university courses). <att>ref</att> is used if the monographic item
                            itself appears in the index of works and then points to its entry. See the below example of a monographic item for an
                            explanation of further elements that may appear inside <gi>monogr</gi>. Afterwards, <gi>imprint</gi> follows using
                                <gi>biblScope</gi>, <gi>pubPlace</gi>, <gi>publisher</gi> and <gi>date</gi>, as specified in the TEI guidelines. For
                            monographic items, <gi>biblStruct</gi> looks as follows: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                <biblStruct xml:id="w...">
                                    <monogr>
                                        <author ref="#p...">...</author>
                                        <editor ref="#p..." role="...">...</editor>
                                        <title level="m">...</title>
                                        <title level="m" type="sub">...</title>
                                        <edition n="...">...</edition>
                                        <editor ref="#p..." role="...">...</editor>
                                        <imprint>
                                            <pubPlace ref="#l...">...</pubPlace>
                                            <publisher>...</publisher>
                                            <date when-iso="..."/>
                                        </imprint>
                                        <extent unit="volume">2</extent>
                                    </monogr>
                                </biblStruct>
                            </egXML> Only <gi>monogr</gi> appears here. Its structure is the same as above. <gi>author</gi> and <gi>editor</gi> are
                            used if appropriate, the position of the latter depending on whether the work as is or only the specific edition was
                            published by the editor. <gi>editor</gi> may use <att>role</att> as specified above. <gi>title</gi> must have the
                            attribute <att>level</att>=”<val>m</val>” denoting that it is monographic item. Sub-titles are added using a further
                                <gi>title</gi> element with the attribute <att>type</att>=”<val>sub</val>”. <gi>edition</gi> is used if appropriate.
                            Towards the end, <gi>imprint</gi> follows with <gi>pubPlace</gi>, <gi>publisher</gi> and <gi>date</gi>. <gi>extent</gi>
                            may be given to denote the size of the item, for example if it has more than one volume. </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Index of contributors</head>
                    <p>Contributors have <att>xml:id</att>s that are composed of their forename, a dot and their surname.</p>
                    <p>It is structured like the index of persons, with a <gi>listPerson</gi> element and multiple <gi>person</gi> element. Inside
                        each <gi>person</gi>, there is three elements : <list>
                            <item><gi>persName</gi>: it contains the <gi>forename</gi> and <gi>surname</gi></item>
                            <item><gi>affiliation</gi>: it contains informations about the institute associated to the contributor, with the
                                    <gi>orgName</gi> element, with an organisation that will have to be declared in the index of organizations and the
                                address for the location of the institute in a <gi>address</gi> element.</item>
                            <item><gi>occupation</gi>: it contains the occupation of the contributor within the project </item>
                        </list>
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                            <person xml:id="floriane.chiffoleau">
                                <persName>
                                    <forename>Floriane</forename>
                                    <surname>Chiffoleau</surname>
                                </persName>
                                <affiliation>
                                    <orgName ref="inria">Institut national de recherche en informatique et automatique (INRIA)</orgName>
                                    <address>
                                        <street>2 rue Simone Iff</street>
                                        <postCode>75012</postCode>
                                        <settlement>Paris</settlement>
                                        <country key="FR">France</country>
                                    </address>
                                </affiliation>
                                <occupation>Encodage du projet</occupation>
                            </person>
                        </egXML></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Encoding decisions for the whole edition</head>
                <p>This section describes encoding decisions for certain elements that appear throughout the whole edition, i. e. in manuscripts as
                    well as in indices and <gi>teiHeader</gi>s.</p>
                <div>
                    <head>Dates</head>
                    <p> Dates can appear inside the elements <gi>date</gi>, <gi>docDate</gi> and <gi>origDate</gi>. We always give an ISO-8601-like
                        standardized form like this: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><date when-iso="1823-10-06">den 6t October.
                                23</date>
                            <date when-iso="1824/1825">1824-1825</date></egXML></p>
                    <p>Inside the indices, there need not be any textual content in most <gi>date</gi> elements because such content is not shown in
                        the web interface anyway.</p>
                    <p>Thus, this is correct: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><birth><date when-iso="1730-08-19"/></birth></egXML> . .
                        . but this is superfluous: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><birth><date when-iso="1730-08-19">19. August
                                    1730</date></birth></egXML></p>
                    <p>Because the TEI guidelines allow a number of attributes and ways of encoding a standardized form of the given date, we have
                        decided not to use all of them, but always encode dates in this format: <list>
                            <item>We always use the attribute <att>when-iso</att> for singular values and give the dates according to ISO 8601, that
                                is to say in the following format: yyyy-mm-dd.</item>
                            <item>When the only date element provided is a year, we will not use <att>when-iso</att> but simply <att>when</att>. We
                                can then have two cases for the use of <att>when</att>. When the year is BC or in early century and it is not
                                completely sure, the date will also have content to indicate approximation. When it is in more recent century, we will
                                only have the date with the attribute.
                                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
                                <date when="0001">ca. 1 CE</date>
                                <date when="1622"/>
                            </egXML></item>
                            <item>For intervals, we use the attribute <att>notBefore</att> and <att>notAfter</att> or their more specific version
                                    <att>notBefore-iso</att> and <att>notAfter-iso</att>. It will depends on the accuracy of the dates. When the
                                interval is two dates in yyyy-mm-dd format, we use the iso form of the attribute and with other cases, we use the
                                plain format. In any of those cases, we will always have content inside the tag to write exactly what the intervals
                                means, in order to display the correct information in the web interface. For example:
                                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
                                    <date notAfter="-0420" notBefore="-0430">between 430 and 420 BCE</date>
                                    <date notAfter="0100" notBefore="0001">2nd century CE</date>
                                    <date notBefore="1824" notAfter="1825">1824-1825</date>
                            </egXML></item>
                            <item>Sometimes, there are also intervals because the encoder is uncertain of the exact date. In those cases, we will used
                                the <att>notBefore</att> and <att>notAfter</att> attribute or the iso format if the uncertainty is between two exact dates.
                                The uncertainty or approximation will be established with the content of the tag, by using words like "or, "probably"
                                or "around". For example:
                                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve">
                                <date notAfter="-0396" notBefore="-0399">probably between 399 and 396 BCE</date>
                                <date notAfter-iso="1799-08-15" notBefore-iso="1799-08-10">10 or 15 August 1799</date>
                                <date notAfter="1805" notBefore="1804">1804 or 1805</date>
                                <date notAfter="1525-01" notBefore="1524-12">December 1524 or January 1525</date>
                            </egXML></item>
                            <item><p>Dates may also refer to a different calendar, mainly to the French Revolutionary calendar. The value of
                                        <att>when-iso</att> always has to be in the form of the Gregorian calendar. The <att>calendar</att> attribute
                                    is used to denote that the date refers to another calendar. We use the value <val>“french-rev-cal”</val> for the
                                    French Revolutionary calendar: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                        <date calendar="french-rev-cal" when-iso="1804-12-12">21 frimaire</date>
                                    </egXML></p></item>
                        </list></p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>XML template for egodocuments</head>
                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                    <TEI>
                        <teiHeader>
                            <fileDesc>
                                <titleStmt>
                                    <title xml:lang="en"/>
                                    <title xml:lang="fr"/>
                                    <funder>Ministry of Higher Education, Research and Innovation</funder>
                                    <principal>
                                        <persName ref="#anne.baillot">
                                            <forename>Anne</forename>
                                            <surname>Baillot</surname>
                                        </persName>
                                        <affiliation>
                                            <orgName ref="#mans.uni">Le Mans Université</orgName>
                                            <address>
                                                <street>Avenue Olivier Messiaen</street>
                                                <postCode>72085</postCode>
                                                <settlement>Le Mans</settlement>
                                                <country key="FR">France</country>
                                            </address>
                                        </affiliation>
                                    </principal>
                                    <respStmt>
                                        <resp>Transcription by</resp>
                                        <persName ref="#name.surname">
                                            <forename/>
                                            <surname/>
                                        </persName>
                                    </respStmt>
                                    <respStmt>
                                        <resp>Encoding by</resp>
                                        <persName ref="#name.surname">
                                            <forename/>
                                            <surname/>
                                        </persName>
                                    </respStmt>
                                    <respStmt>
                                        <resp>Digitization by</resp>
                                        <orgName ref="#"/>
                                    </respStmt>
                                </titleStmt>
                                <publicationStmt>
                                    <authority/>
                                    <availability>
                                        <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/deed.en">Attribution 3.0 Unported (CC BY 3.0)
                                        </licence>
                                    </availability>
                                    <date when-iso=""/>
                                </publicationStmt>
                                <seriesStmt>
                                    <title type="main"/>
                                    <title type="genre"/>
                                    <title type="topic"/>
                                    <title type="topic"/>
                                </seriesStmt>
                                <sourceDesc>
                                    <msDesc>
                                        <msIdentifier>
                                            <location>
                                                <address>
                                                    <street/>
                                                    <postCode/>
                                                    <settlement/>
                                                    <region/>
                                                    <country key=" "/>
                                                </address>
                                            </location>
                                            <institution ref="# "/>
                                            <repository/>
                                            <collection/>
                                            <idno/>
                                        </msIdentifier>
                                        <msContents>
                                            <msItem>
                                                <docDate when=" "/>
                                                <note resp="#name.surname"/>
                                                <note type="keyword" resp="#name.surname"/>
                                            </msItem>
                                        </msContents>
                                        <physDesc>
                                            <objectDesc>
                                                <supportDesc>
                                                    <support>
                                                        <material/>
                                                    </support>
                                                    <extent>
                                                        <measure type="folio" xml:lang="fr"/>
                                                        <measure type="folio" xml:lang="en"/>
                                                        <dimensions unit="cm">
                                                            <height/>
                                                            <width/>
                                                        </dimensions>
                                                    </extent>
                                                    <foliation>
                                                        <p xml:lang="fr"/>
                                                        <p xml:lang="en"/>
                                                    </foliation>
                                                    <condition>
                                                        <p xml:lang="fr"/>
                                                        <p xml:lang="en"/>
                                                    </condition>
                                                </supportDesc>
                                                <layoutDesc>
                                                    <layout xml:id="ref_letterhead">
                                                        <p xml:lang="fr"/>
                                                        <p xml:lang="en"/>
                                                    </layout>
                                                </layoutDesc>
                                            </objectDesc>
                                            <handDesc>
                                                <handNote xml:id="major_hand" scope=" " medium=" " scribe=" " scribeRef="# ">
                                                    <p xml:lang="fr"/>
                                                    <p xml:lang="en"/>
                                                </handNote>
                                                <handNote xml:id="" scope=" " medium=" " scribe=" " scribeRef="# " corresp="#">
                                                    <p xml:lang="fr"/>
                                                    <p xml:lang="en"/>
                                                </handNote>
                                            </handDesc>
                                            <additions>
                                                <p xml:lang="fr"/>
                                                <p xml:lang="en"/>
                                            </additions>
                                            <!-- <accMat>
                                            <p xml:lang="fr">La lettre est accompagnée de ... </p>
                                            <p xml:lang="en">The letter also contains .. </p>
                                        </accMat> -->
                                        </physDesc>
                                        <history>
                                            <origin>
                                                <p xml:lang="fr">La lettre a été écrite à <origPlace> </origPlace> le <origDate when-iso=" "
                                                    > </origDate></p>
                                                <p xml:lang="en">The letter has been written in <origPlace> </origPlace> on <origDate
                                                        when-iso="{date}"> </origDate></p>
                                            </origin>
                                            <acquisition>
                                                <p xml:lang="fr"/>
                                                <p xml:lang="en"/>
                                            </acquisition>
                                        </history>
                                        <additional>
                                            <listBibl>
                                                <bibl>
                                                    <bibl xml:lang="fr"/>
                                                    <bibl xml:lang="en"/>
                                                </bibl>
                                            </listBibl>
                                        </additional>
                                    </msDesc>
                                </sourceDesc>
                            </fileDesc>
                            <encodingDesc>
                                <projectDesc>
                                    <p xml:lang="fr">L'encodage de ce document s'est fait dans le cadre du projet DAHN d'"Éditions numérique de
                                        manuscrits historiques (correspondances)"</p>
                                    <p xml:lang="en">The encoding of this document is part of the DAHN Project "Digital Editions of historical
                                        manuscripts (correspondences)"</p>
                                </projectDesc>
                                <editorialDecl>
                                    <correction>
                                        <p xml:lang="fr">Aucune correction</p>
                                        <p xml:lang="en">No correction</p>
                                    </correction>
                                    <hyphenation eol="all" rend="sh">
                                        <p xml:lang="fr">Toutes les coupures de mots pour fin de ligne (indiquées principalement avec un tiret simple)
                                            ont été conservées.</p>
                                        <p xml:lang="en">All the end-of-line hyphenation (made with a single hyphen) have been kept</p>
                                    </hyphenation>
                                </editorialDecl>
                            </encodingDesc>
                            <profileDesc>
                                <correspDesc>
                                    <correspAction type="sent">
                                        <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/"/>
                                        <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/"/>
                                        <date when-iso=" "/>
                                    </correspAction>
                                    <correspAction type="received">
                                        <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/"/>
                                        <!-- <placeName ref="https://www.geonames.org/"/> -->
                                    </correspAction>
                                    <correspContext>
                                        <ref type="prev" target=".xml"/>
                                        <ref type="next" target=".xml"/>
                                    </correspContext>
                                </correspDesc>
                                <langUsage>
                                    <language ident="fr"/>
                                </langUsage>
                            </profileDesc>
                            <revisionDesc status="proposed">
                                <change when-iso=" " who="# "/>
                            </revisionDesc>
                        </teiHeader>
                        <text>
                            <body>
                                <div type="transcription">
                                    <pb n="" facs=".JPG"/>
                                </div>
                            </body>
                        </text>
                    </TEI>
                </egXML>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>List of the modules used on my TEI files</head>
                <schemaSpec ident="myTEI" docLang="en" prefix="tei_" xml:lang="en">
                    <moduleRef key="core" except="email gloss headItem headLabel meeting postBox said"/>
                    <moduleRef key="tei" except=""/>
                    <moduleRef key="header"
                        except="appInfo application cRefPattern catDesc category classCode classDecl conversion listChange listPrefixDef samplingDecl scriptNote styleDefDecl tagUsage tagsDecl taxonomy unitDecl unitDef"/>
                    <moduleRef key="textstructure"
                        except="div1 div2 div3 div4 div5 div6 div7 docAuthor docEdition docImprint docTitle group imprimatur titlePage titlePart"/>
                    <moduleRef key="namesdates" except=""/>
                    <moduleRef key="transcr"
                        except="am damage damageSpan ex line mod path redo restore retrace secl sourceDoc substJoin surfaceGrp surplus undo"/>
                    <moduleRef key="msdescription"
                        except="adminInfo colophon custEvent custodialHist depth dim filiation finalRubric heraldry incipit locus locusGrp msFrag msPart musicNotation recordHist rubric scriptDesc secFol signatures surrogates typeDesc typeNote"/>
                    <moduleRef key="linking" include="ab anchor link linkGrp seg"/>
                    <moduleRef key="figures" except="formula notatedMusic"/>
                    <moduleRef key="spoken" include="kinesic vocal"/>
                    <moduleRef key="drama" include="castItem castList role roleDesc"/>
                    <moduleRef key="gaiji" include="g"/>
                    <moduleRef key="analysis" include="pc"/>
                    <elementSpec ident="msIdentifier" mode="change">
                        <content>
                            <sequence>
                                <sequence>
                                    <classRef key="model.placeStateLike" expand="sequenceOptional"/>
                                    <elementRef key="institution" minOccurs="0"/>
                                    <elementRef key="repository" minOccurs="0"/>
                                    <elementRef key="collection" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="unbounded"/>
                                    <elementRef key="idno" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="unbounded"/>
                                </sequence>
                                <alternate minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="unbounded">
                                    <elementRef key="msName"/>
                                    <elementRef key="objectName"/>
                                    <elementRef key="altIdentifier"/>
                                </alternate>
                            </sequence>
                        </content>
                    </elementSpec>
                    <elementSpec ident="add" mode="change">
                        <attList>
                            <attDef ident="place" mode="change">
                                <valList type="semi" mode="replace">
                                    <valItem ident="across">
                                        <desc>across the line (used with del rend="overwritten")</desc>
                                    </valItem>
                                    <valItem ident="below">
                                        <desc>below the line</desc>
                                    </valItem>
                                    <valItem ident="bottom">
                                        <desc>at the foot of the page</desc>
                                    </valItem>
                                    <valItem ident="margin">
                                        <desc>in the margin (left, right, or both)</desc>
                                    </valItem>
                                    <valItem ident="top">
                                        <desc>at the top of the page</desc>
                                    </valItem>
                                    <valItem ident="opposite">
                                        <desc>on the opposite, i.e. facing, page</desc>
                                    </valItem>
                                    <valItem ident="overleaf">
                                        <desc>on the other side of the leaf</desc>
                                    </valItem>
                                    <valItem ident="above">
                                        <desc>above the line</desc>
                                    </valItem>
                                    <valItem ident="end">
                                        <desc>at the end of e.g. chapter or volume.</desc>
                                    </valItem>
                                    <valItem ident="inline">
                                        <desc>within the body of the text.</desc>
                                    </valItem>
                                    <valItem ident="inspace">
                                        <desc>in a predefined space, for example left by an earlier scribe.</desc>
                                    </valItem>
                                    <valItem ident="dots">
                                        <desc>if the text was first deleted and then marked to be included again by writing dots below it</desc>
                                    </valItem>
                                </valList>
                            </attDef>
                        </attList>
                    </elementSpec>
                    <elementSpec ident="del" mode="change">
                        <attList>
                            <attDef ident="rend" mode="change">
                                <valList type="semi" mode="replace">
                                    <valItem ident="overwritten">
                                        <desc>a correction has been written over it (used with add place="across")</desc>
                                    </valItem>
                                    <valItem ident="strikethrough">
                                        <desc>horizontal or vertical line(s) through a word/expression</desc>
                                    </valItem>
                                    <valItem ident="erasure">
                                        <desc>indication of removed word in the text (usually indistinguishable)</desc>
                                    </valItem>
                                    <valItem ident="none">
                                        <desc>if the deletion is only marked by writing the correct word alongside</desc>
                                    </valItem>
                                </valList>
                            </attDef>
                        </attList>
                    </elementSpec>
                </schemaSpec>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
